<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the preparation to the crosse, and to deathe and of the comforte vnder the crosse and death, two bokes very fruictefull for deuoute people to rede, translated from latyn to englysshe, by Rycharde Tracy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1540</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 105 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109824</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845468</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10370</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01278)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10370)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 67:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the preparation to the crosse, and to deathe and of the comforte vnder the crosse and death, two bokes very fruictefull for deuoute people to rede, translated from latyn to englysshe, by Rycharde Tracy.</title>
                  <author>Frith, John, 1503-1533, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Tracy, Richard, d. 1569.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[216] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Thomæ Bertheleti typis impress. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D.XL. [1540]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed, doubtfully, to John Frith.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 has caption title, reading: The preparation to deathe, and howe they which be in point of deathe, shulde be comforted, the. ii. boke.</note>
                  <note>Running title to part 1 reads:  Preparation to the crosse; running title to part 2 reads:  Preparation to deathe.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-O.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10370:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10370:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> OF THE PREPARATION TO THE CROSSE,</hi> and to Deathe, and of the comforte vnder the croſſe and deathe, two bokes very fruictefull for deuoute people to rede, tranſlated from latyn to englyſſhe, by Rycharde Tracy.</p>
            <p>1534</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10370:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10370:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RYGHT HONORABLE, AND HIS</hi> ſyngular good lorde and mayſter, Lord Thomas Crumwel, Lorde Priuy ſeale, Rycharde Tracy deſyreth and wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth bodely proſperous helth, and to the ſoule eternall lyfe and felycitie.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN</hi> I conſider the weake frailtie of man, and howe naturallye we be ſubiecte to many troubles, aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and temptations, as well of the body as of the ſoule, and alſo when I call to my remembraunce the wordes of Chriſte, ſpoken to his elect,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> That in this world they ſhulde ſuffer perſecution and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and lykewyſe the ſayinge of the apoſtel Paule,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> That al they
<pb facs="tcp:10370:3"/> whiche wyll lyue godly in Chriſte Ieſu, muſte ſuffer perſecution: I thynke ſurely, that euery chryſten man dothe expect Chriſtes promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and conſtantly beleueth, that the ſcriptures ſhalbe fulfilled and founde true. Wherfore ſeing there is no euaſion nor meane, to eſcape the aduerſities, temptations, and croſſe, whiche god ſhal laye on the ſhulders of his electe, and nature is ſo inconſtant, frayl, and weake, that of our own myght and power we are not able to reſyſte, nor can not wyllyngely and paciently ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyne and beare ſuch aduerſities, and croſſe, it behoueth euery chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten man, to ſerch out and prouide ſome godly conſolation and reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to comforte and make ſtronge his mynde, that he may paciently ſuffer all tribulation, all tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:3"/> al aduerſitie, which god ſhal ſende to hym, alwaye reknowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge, that there is no power but of god, and that god wyl not ſend to his electe any ſuche croſſe, but therwith he wyll alſo gyue grace and meane paciently to ſuffer the ſame, ſo that he ſhall not be found diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the good wyl of god. Of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortes agaynſt the croſſe of tribulation, one in eſpeciall of late I founde. Not a yere paſte it pleaſed God to ſende me ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe tribulations, whiche were to ſtronge for Nature to ſuffer and beare pacientely: but my chaunce was ſo good, throughe the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prouydence of god, that in my troubles this lyttel boke was ſent me from a frende: whiche when I had red ouer, and delyberately per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uſed,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:4"/> it animated &amp; made me ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g not onely pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to ſuffer al mine aduerſities, but alſo for theym to gyue god ryghte hartye thankes, that it wolde pleaſe hym of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundante mercy and goodneſſe to remembre me, his miſerable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with his ſo erneſt a token and moſte ſure pledge of his godly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and loue, accordynge to his promyſe,<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.</note> which is, whom the lord loueth, hym he chaſteneth, yea and he ſcourgeth euery ſonne that he receyueth. For in the readynge of this boke, I receyued ſuche conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, that I thought it moſte neceſſary, yea and expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent (ſeinge I haue by experyence felte, what good fruyte commeth therof) to tranſlate the ſame in to englyſhe, and ſo to put it forthe in
<pb facs="tcp:10370:4"/> printe, that it myghte be the more common, and that many chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge to fall into lyke croſſe of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, maye be partakers and optein like conſolation, as I haue receiued therby. And I haue dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated this boke to you my ſyngu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler good lorde &amp; maſter, for as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as I euydently perceyue, that you are endewed not onely with godly knowledge and doctryne, but alſo haue a right ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t zeale, good mynd, and deſyre to ſet forth all ſuche thynge as may be for the vtilitie helpe and comforte of the hole congregation and churche of this realme. Therfore with al hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie I deſyre your accuſtomed benignitie to accept this the firſte fruite and labour of me your pore ſeruant, which am, and ſhall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:10370:5"/> redy and glad with al dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to do you the ſeruice that I can, &amp; dayly pray almyghty god, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue you in longe lyfe, welth, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and proſperitie. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:10370:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>THE PREPA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATION TO THE</hi> croſſe, and howe it muſte be paciently borne.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR</hi> as moche as Chriſte comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to denye ourſelues, and to folowe hym, and ſuffer the croſſe, he commaundeth vs alſo, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare vs to ſuffer the croſſe paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, ſayinge:<note place="margin">Matth. 16.</note> If any man wyll come after me, let hym denye hym ſelfe, and take vp my croſſe, and folowe me. And who ſo euer doth not beare my croſſe, and folowe me, can not be my diſcyple. Soo councelleth the wiſe man, ſaying:<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.</note> Sonne, whan thou doeſt come to the ſeruice of god, ſtande in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſenes and feare, and prepare thy ſoule to ſuffer temptation. but
<pb facs="tcp:10370:6"/> bycauſe there be dyuers croſſes, ne leſt a man paraduenture ſhuld take a ſtraunge croſſe, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth not to hym, that is to ſay, ſhulde feine to him ſelfe newe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, as preſcript dayes of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge, vowed chaſtitie, ſhurtes of heare, diſgyſed garmentes, and ſuch other trifles, which god hath not commaunded: therfore Chriſt hath put to this terme, <hi>ſciliceth (his owne)</hi> whiche is as moche to ſaye, that euery man ſtudy to mortifie his owne fleſhe, &amp; the ſynne, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che reygneth in him, beinge euer redy to ſuffer what ſoo euer god dothe ſende hym.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶What the croſſe is. Cap. i.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A CROSSE</hi> is euery afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and tribulation, or eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry aduerſitie and heuines ſent by
<pb facs="tcp:10370:6"/> god, to euery kynde of lyuynge, throughe faythe, and the word of god: when that euery thyng doth not proſpere, euen as a man wold haue it: whiche in ſome place is called lernynge, or correction, and temptation, a rodde, and a ſtaffe. Wherfore it is a foliſhe and an he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uy croſſe, whiche we by our owne preſumption do take vpon vs not commaunded of god, as the prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of Ball, and all hypocrites do take vppon them. But that is the trewe croſſe, whiche god doth lay vpon vs, whiche when it is layed vpon vs, we ſuffer paciently, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body in his vocation and kynd of lyuinge, as to gette our breade with the ſweate of our counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and women to bring forthe theyr chyldren in peynes, to ſuffer paciently the good wil of the lord,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:7"/> to mortifie our mortall membres vppon the erthe, to be euer buſily occupied in the commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the lord, and for the word of god, to ſuffer al ſcornes, and moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, lyes, perſecutions, and not to feare the moſte cruell, ye euen the moſt ſhameful death. Therfore to ſuffer a croſſe, is nothing els, then to ſuffer pacientely, what ſo euer come to vs, by the godly and bene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uolent wyll of the lorde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Two kyndes of croſſes. Cap. ii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THERE BE</hi> two kyndes of croſſes, the oone a ſtraunge croſſe, the other our owne, the one of the faythefull, the other of the wycked. for the vnfeythful be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, that they may be an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of theyr owne iniquytie, and that they be perpetually condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:
<pb facs="tcp:10370:7"/> but the feythful be puniſhed, that they maye be made ſtronge, and that the lorde be gloryfied in them. So ſtrange puniſhementes be a warninge to put the faythful in mynde of the good wyll of the lorde. For the lorde doth punyſhe ſome in this lyfe, that he may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke ſuche as maye be made hole to repentaunce, as the ſcripture ſaythe:<note place="margin">Prou. 19.</note> When the mocker or ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is punyſhed, the vnlerned is made wyſer.<note place="margin">Gen. 8.</note> So the angell dydde ſhewe Abraham, what ſhulde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Sodomites, that he myght teache his chyldren the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement of god. Alſo Chriſte ſaith,<note place="margin">Luc. 13.</note> that all ſhal peryſhe, as they were kylled of Pylate, if that they doo not repente.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10370:8"/>
               <head>¶Howe the feythfull be tempted. Capi. iii.</head>
               <p>THe faythful be tempted with a natural and ſpiritual tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, an outward &amp; an inward, that is of the fleſhe, of the worlde, and of the dyuell. For the croſſe ſignifieth as wel the inward tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as the outwarde. Of the fyrſte ſpeketh the apoſtell,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> Let no temptation take you, excepte the naturall temptation, that is eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſecution, whiche maye hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in this worlde, whiche dothe not hurte the lyfe, but rather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh to the bleſſed lyfe: but the ſpirituall or inwarde temptation, is the inwarde feare of ſynne and deathe, it is the afflyction or temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation of the conſcience, ſuch tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations be mooſte greuouſe, and where god is not, they brynge the
<pb facs="tcp:10370:8"/> tempted to deathe eternal. Of the whiche Paule to the Hebrewes ſaythe: It is impoſſible that they,<note place="margin">Hebre. 6.</note> whiche ones be enlyghtened, and haue taſted the good word of god and the vertue of the worlde to come, if they ſlyde and fall agayn, to be renued by repentaunce: as Demas, Hymeneus, and Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, profeſſynge the faythe, dyd fall from it. and that is ſynne to deathe, ſynne in the holy gooſte, ſynne of vnbelefe, ſynne of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall pryde. Wherfore Chriſt dyd commande vs to pray,<note place="margin">Luc. 11.</note> Let vs not be led into temptation. They that beleue, do ſynne, but they fal not vtterly away: ſo that they conſent not to the fleſhe, the world, and the deuil, but by the grace of god they be preſerued and go awaye, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge victory and triumphe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10370:9"/>
               <head>¶The croſſe is of god onely. Cap. iiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FYRSTE,</hi> we muſte conſider, that in all our afflictions, no calamitie or penſiuenes falleth on vs by fortune or chaunce, but by the appoynted councell of god, by his wyll and ſufferaunce, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth holy ſcripture.<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> Feare not, for god commeth not, but for to trie vs.<note place="margin">Deut. 13.</note> The lord your god trieth you, to make it knowen, whether ye loue or not.<note place="margin">Iob. 9.</note> The lorde hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the lorde hath taken awaye. The lorde kylleth,<note place="margin">1. Samu. 2.</note> and gyueth life agayne, he bryngeth euen to hell, and backe agayne.<note place="margin">Prouer. 3.</note> Refuſe not the chaſtiſing of god, neyther grudge thou when he correcteth the. For whom god loueth, he correcteth: and yet delyteth noo leſſe then the father in the chylde.<note place="margin">Pſal. 65.</note> for thou haſt proued vs o god, and haſte tryed
<pb facs="tcp:10370:9"/> vs, as the ſyluer is tryed by fyer. Thou haſt ledde vs into a ſnare, thou haſt laden our backes ful of troubles, thou haſte appoynted me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be heades ouer vs, we haue paſſed thorow fier and water, and yet haſt thou refreſhed vs.<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> It is for my welthe, that thou haſte broughte me vnder, to lerne thy ryghteouſeneſſe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 20.</note> Bleſſed is that man, which is vnder the loue and nurture of the lorde.<note place="margin">Hiere. 31.</note> Thou haſte ſtryken me, and I haue repented, thou haſt chaſtened me lorde, and I am taughte as one vnder age, wylde, and vntamed.<note place="margin">Threno. 3</note> Whoo can ſay, that any thynge, can be done, without the lordes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente? From the mouthe of the hygheſt gothe there not good and yll? By which ſaying the prophet rebuketh the wycked, whiche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:10"/> that afflictions happen by the councell and prouydence of god. Suche alſo rebuketh Sophon,<note place="margin">Sopho. 1.</note> I ſhall viſet men drowned in theyr dregges, whiche ſay in theyr har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, The lorde wyll not doo bothe good &amp; yll.<note place="margin">Matth. 10.</note> Are not two ſparowes ſolde for a farthynge, and yet not one of them falleth on the erthe, without the wil of your father?<note place="margin">Roma. 11.</note> Al thynges are of hym, by hym, and in hym.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> While we iudged, we are puniſhed of the lord, leſt we ſhuld with the world be condemned.</p>
               <p>¶It is vndoubtedly noo ſmalle comforte, to be aſſured, that the croſſe is of god, and that we are chaſtened of god, and not of the dyuell, or els of any wycked man: which vtterly can haue no power vpon vs, not ſo moch as to moue one heare of our hed, beſyde the
<pb facs="tcp:10370:10"/> wyll of the lorde, without the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feraunce of god, as Chryſte hym ſelfe comforteth vs, ſaying,<note place="margin">Matth. 10.</note> Euen the heares of your headde are all nombred. As thoughe he ſhoulde ſaye, if god be carefull for the ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, how moche more ſhal he be carefull for you? whiche are his people and ſhepe of his paſture, that nothyng happen raſhely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, without his beneuolente wyll. Seinge alſo that the dyuell had no power vpon ſwyne, moch leſſe vppon them that are godly, whom he can not hurt at al.<note place="margin">Matth. 9.</note> for ſo the eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſtes wryte, that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelles prayed Chriſte, and ſayde, If thou caſte vs forthe,<note place="margin">Marc. 5.</note> ſuffer vs to enter into the herde of ſwyne. And he ſayde vnto them, Goo ye. They haue then no power vppon the holye, no trewely not on the
<pb facs="tcp:10370:11"/> ſwyne, excepte that god ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them, no they dare not, nor can not any thynge agaynſt them, but by the ſufferaunce of god. for god alone bindeth this dragon, and he alone louſeth him, as Chriſt ſaith, No man can enter into the houſe of a ſtronge man,<note place="margin">Marc. 3.</note> and ſpoyle him of his veſſell and treaſure, oneles he fyrſte bynde the ſtronge man. For the dyuel is chayned &amp; bound ſo ſtrayghtly, that he may do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge, before that god appoynt hym,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> as it is written in Iob. The lorde ſayde to Satan, Lo, al that he hath, are in thy hande, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende not thy hande vppon hym. Satan dothe nothynge, but that, that god ſuffereth and wyll. Alſo all the godly (as the ſonnes of god) are euer in goddes preſence. For whome the lorde euer careth
<pb facs="tcp:10370:11"/> for, tenderynge them, nuryſhyng them, kepynge and defendynge them, from all yll. what greatter comfort then can there be of faith, as a ſure rocke, then that the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ar well aſſured and know, them ſelues euermore ſet before the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des eyes, and to be kept vnder his hande? Can myſery oppreſſe the? can the croſſe? can ſinne? can deth? can hell? Be aſſured, that thou art in the preſence of god. they ſhall not preuayle, the lorde careth for the, the lordes eye is dyrected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the. whom then ſhalt thou feare, if by faythe thou be made the ſonne of god? God careth for the, yea and ſendeth his aungel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les to kepe and defend the, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the wytnes of Dauid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.</note> He hath commaunde his aungels of the, to kepe the in all thy wayes.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:12"/> The aungell of the lorde ſhall be ſente abrode, among al them that feare hym, and ſhal delyuer them. And if god giue lybertie to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, to tempte vs, let vs ſurelye beleue, that with that temptation god ſhall gyue increaſe: that is, that the temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall be for our welthe and profytte, and that we ſhalbe able to ſuffer.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> He ſhal ſtrike and his handes ſhall make hole. Temptations alſo haue theyr ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittes,<note place="margin">Iob. 5.</note> nother can they ouerpaſſe theyr ende appoynted. And as the ſee is compaſſed rounde with bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, euen ſo haue al croſſes their borders and endes, beyonde the whiche they maye not ouerpaſſe. Let euery one therfore, whiche is of god, and beleueth in god, kepe him ſelfe: and the wicked or yl ſhal not touche hym.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.</note> For that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb facs="tcp:10370:12"/> wily crafteſman gothe forth and tempteth the godly, as he tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted Dauid, Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and Peter, with a thouſande ſnares: but he hath neuer the victory. In the croſſe or temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, god hath one purpoſe, and the dyuel an other. Wherfore there ar two kyndes of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation, bothe common to the godlye and vngodly, although dyuerſly. The one kinde is, when god trieth men with moch aduerſitie, that as wel the mekenes, as the faythe of the godly, maye ſhyne forthe, and be made more open, not to other one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but to theym ſelues alſo: and contrary wyſe, that the wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the wycked, (whiche they without ſhame deny, or els vnder ſome falſe colour of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cloke) may openly apere, and alſo be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. The other kynde is, when
<pb facs="tcp:10370:13"/> we are tempted by ſuggeſtions of the dyuell, and affections of the fleſhe, and oftentimes vnder ſuch temptations they fall and lye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, where ſome ſo fall to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge deathe, that they neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſe agayn, other after their fal ar made more lowe and more ware. God therfore correcteth, to make hole, and not to dyſtroye: he pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſheth the godly, for that they ſhuld not be condemned with this frowarde worlde, to proue and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe theyr fayth, to mortifie their fleſſhe, and to kendell in theym a more feruent deſyre of the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge lyfe to come: laſt of all, leſt they ſhuld by reaſon of great gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, be blowen vp with pride: and therby they are proued alſo, to be the very trewe ſonnes of god, and not vnlauful and baſtardes. But
<pb facs="tcp:10370:13"/> the dyuel tempteth to diſtroy, and to drawe into deſperation and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>belefe.<note place="margin">Luc. 22. Act. 5.</note> He roted in the hart of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, to deliuer vp Chriſt. He tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Ananias and Saphira, and had the maſtry. He tempted Iob,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.2.</note> and was redy to deſtroy hym, if he had ben ſoo ſuffered.<note place="margin">Matth. 4.</note> He tempted Chriſt, but he preuayled nothing. He was buſy with the apoſtels, to ſyfte them as wheate, but the lord prayed, and he wanne nothynge. He ſtyrred vp Dauid to number Iſraell, he obeyed the temtation,<note place="margin">Para. 22.</note> and brake the precept of god. So Peter forſware Chryſte, and yet they obteyned mercye. Thus he runneth about, ſekynge whom he may deuoure. So the godly ouer come in temptation, althoughe ſomtyme through the good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell and prouydence of god, they
<pb facs="tcp:10370:14"/> be ouercome: but al thinges wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth with them to their welth, and for the beſt. Wherfore we pray our father, that he leade vs not in to temptation, that he wyl not tempt vs aboue that we ſhall be able to beare, but to make with the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation increaſe, and delyuer vs from yll. Satan therfore nor da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth nor can do any thing againſt the holy, but by gods ſufferance. Al thynges are done after goddes arbitrye or wyll, withoute whoſe becke or graunt, no aduerſitie can happen. God ſendeth afflictions, ſomtyme by him ſelfe through his owne wyl onely, ſometyme by his minyſters, for he bothe dyſtroyeth the wicked with the countenance of his wrothe, and alſo by contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry angelles and perſecutours he ſuffereth his ſonnes to be exercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:14"/> For god gyueth power ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme to the dyuell, to aſſaute the ryghtuouſe man: but bycauſe his curſednes is inſaciable, tyll he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure a man all together, there is a lawe preſcribed vnto him, beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the whiche he may not tempt. For god is faythefull, and meaſureth our fyghte or battayle accordyng to our ſtrengthes. wherfore let no mannes hart fayle hym, god kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, howe farre it is expedyente, that our mekeneſſe be exercyſed, that from henſeforth, we maye be mete to do greatter thynges. For vndoubtedly if god had not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen the ſtrength and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancie of Iob his ſouldiour, he wolde not haue gyuen ſo moche lybertie to Satan, agaynſt him, ſodenly and at ones to deſpoyle, one ſo ryche, ſo bleſſed of al his ſubſtance, and
<pb facs="tcp:10370:15"/> to plucke hym from all his felyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. After we are wel taught theſe thynges of goddes prudencie, we ſhall the eaſier beare the croſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Croſſe is the worke of the good wyll and mercy of god. Cap. v.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT IS</hi> not inoughe, to fele and conſyder, that we are afflycted throughe the councell and wyll of god, but we muſt moreouer mark the cauſe and intente of his godly wyll, for reaſon iudgeth, that we ar puniſhed, to the ende to be hurt or dyſtroyed: and examples lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moue vs, of them that haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> puniſhed and caſt of from god, as of Pharao, Saul, and other lyke, but we muſt forſake reaſon, and fle ſuch examples, and cleaue to the worde of god. The word of god teacheth, that we ſuffer affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:15"/> to our helth and ſaluation. For afflictions are not ſignes of wrathe and diſpleaſure, but of grace and fauour. God calleth to repentaunce, and by affliction he in a maner ſpeketh and declareth, that he wyll forgyue. For as bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, or eatynge of the lordes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, do wytneſſe vnto vs, that we are forgyuen: euen ſo nerehande affliction maye be called a certain ſacrament. For it ſygnifieth, that god wyll forgyue. And why doth it ſo ſignifie? for euen as other ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes haue the worde of the element: ſo to afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the word annexed, wherby is promyſed grace, for ſoo ſayth Paule.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> while we are puniſhed, we are corrected of the lorde, leaſte we ſhulde with this world be condempned. Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion calleth to repentaunce, that
<pb facs="tcp:10370:16"/> we peryſhe not. And he correcteth the ſonne,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> whome he loueth. It is good for me, that thou haſte broughte me vnder, that I maye lerne thy rightuouſenes.<note place="margin">Eſai. 26.</note> Lord in tribulation haue they viſited the: it is thy lerning to them, that they ſhulde crie to the in anguiſhe and ſorowe.<note place="margin">Eſai. 28.</note> Trouble gyueth vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng agayne. To the ende to doo his owne worke, he dothe an other worke. that is, to the intent to make ſafe, he chaſteneth and ſcourgeth.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> A troubled ſpirite is a ſacrifice to god. A ſacrifice is that that pleaſeth god. Wherfore for ſo moch as affliction pleaſeth god it ſignifieth not thoſe which ar af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, to be reproued, and caſt of from god, for he wyl not the death of a ſynner,<note place="margin">Ezech. 33.</note> but that he conuerte and lyue. We muſt therfore in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction
<pb facs="tcp:10370:16"/> ſtedfaſtly beleue, that our trouble commeth not by chaunce, but that it is gouerned of god. Moreouer, that god wyll not vs therfore to be troubled, to hurte and dyſtroy vs, but to calle vs to repentaunce, to exercyſe vs and ſaue vs, as holy ſcripture euerye where declareth.<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.</note> He wyll not ſtyll be angry, he wyll not continually threten vs. He hath begonne,<note place="margin">Hoſie. 6.</note> and wyll make vs ſafe, he ſhall ſtryke and make vs hole.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 144.</note> The lorde lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp al them that fal, and pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vp all thoſe whiche are broi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.<note place="margin">Eſai. 49.</note> Can the woman forgette her babe, that ſhe haue not compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the chylde of her wombe? And if ſhe be forgetfull, yet wyll not I forget the.<note place="margin">Matt. 16.</note> So Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth his. The womanne, when ſhe bryngeth forthe:<note place="margin">Eſai. 46.</note> whiche are
<pb facs="tcp:10370:17"/> borne of my wombe, whiche are borne of my bealy, euen to the old age I my ſelfe wyll carie, euen to the hoore heares, I haue done it, and I wyll beare, I wyl cary and make ſafe.<note place="margin">Mich. 4.</note> Morne and be buſy o doughter of Sion, as a woman traueylinge, for nowe thou ſhalte go forthe from the citie, and ſhalt dwell in a region, and ſhalte come euen to Babilon, there ſhalt thou be delyuered, there ſhall the lorde redeme the.<note place="margin">Iob. 33.</note> Teachynge them, he inſtructeth with lernyng, to pluck a man from thoſe thinges, which he hath done, and to delyuer hym frome pryde.<note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> So Abraham was tempted to be tried, that his faith mought be made noble and mani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſt, he tempted hym, and ſetteth forthe before vs ſuche example to folowe, when he tempteth and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:10370:17"/> our faythe.<note place="margin">Iob. 1.2.</note> So Iob was tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the lorde, that his faythe mought be made more clere. So Dauid,<note place="margin">2. Par. 13. Tobi. 2.</note> ſo Manaſſes on euery ſide vexed, repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted. Alſo Tobias was therfore made blynde, to gyue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of pacience, to his after co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers. Likewiſe Iudith. we ought to be myndfull, howe our fathers were tempted, to be tried.<note place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> Soo it happened in the woman of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan.<note place="margin">Matth. 9.</note> And to the womanne labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge with the iſſue of bloud. by whiche examples we are taughte and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed, to be plucked from god by no temptations, by no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, by no chaſtiſynges, be they neuer ſo great: but the more that god tempteth vs, chaſteneth, and repelleth, ſo moche the more let vs crye to hym, tyll he gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly here vs. It is therfore noo
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10370:18"/>
               <head>¶The godly are the fyrſt that are afflicted, and they are afflicted of god, to theyr good and welthe. Cap. vi.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hiere. 25. et. 49.</note>
                  <hi>LO IN</hi> the citie, in whiche my name is called vpon, begin I to puniſſhe, and ſhall ye be as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentes, and without punyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente?<note place="margin">Ezechi. 9.</note> The lorde commaunded them that diſtroyed Hieruſalem, to begyn at his ſainctuarye.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> The tyme is now, that iugement muſt begyn at the houſe of god. If the iudgement of god begynne at the godly, what ende taryeth theym, whiche beleue not the goſpell of god? but the godly, when they are puniſhed, they ar puniſhed of god to theyr welthe and good, as the epiſtell wrytten to the Hebrewes, dothe clerely teſtifie.<note place="margin">Hebre. 12.</note> Whome the lord loueth, him he correcteth. and he beateth euery chylde whom he
<pb facs="tcp:10370:18"/> receyueth. if ye ſuffer chaſtiſynge, god offereth hym ſelfe vnto you, as to his ſonnes. What ſonne is he, whom the father chaſteth not? If ye be withoute chaſteſynge, whoſe partakers ar al the ſonnes, then are ye ſeruauntes, and noo ſonnes at al. So Salomon:<note place="margin">Prou. 3.</note> The chaſteninge of god thou ſhalt not refuſe, and neyther grudge thou, when he ſhal correct the, for whom the lord loueth, hym he correcteth, and delyteth hym ſelfe, as the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſonne.<note place="margin">Apoc. 3.</note> Whom ſo euer I loue, I rebuke, and chaſte. The godly therfore ar chaſtened of the mercifull god, to theyr welth and good, and thoſe whiche are moſte corrected, are moſte loued of god. As Tobias was chaſtned for his profyte.<note place="margin">Tobi. 2. Gen. 37.</note> Ioſeph throughe the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his brethern, was made
<pb facs="tcp:10370:19"/> ruler of Egypt.<note place="margin">Exod. 1.</note> By reaſon of the tyranny of Pharao, the chyldren of Iſraell encreaſed, and were made innumerable.<note place="margin">Num. 21.</note> The people hurt of ſerpentes cried. So he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicteth the holy bicauſe they ſhuld not be in ſecurite without al feare but that theyr repentance ſhal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, &amp; theyr faith be confyrmed, when they fele them ſelues to be holpe: Although we knowe, that no man is ſcourged of god, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his deſeruyng.<note place="margin">Roma. 3.</note> For euery man is a lier and a ſinner, and no fleſhe ſhall be iuſtified before the face of god.<note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> For all fleſhe hath corrupted his way. Wherfore al fleſhe is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and yet we knowe that not alway the godly are puniſhed for ſynnes, but ſomtyme to proue the fayth of the afflicted. As Iob, Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid, and many other, or to declare
<pb facs="tcp:10370:19"/> and make manifeſt the maieſtie of his name. Soo he punyſſhed the Iſraelites in Egypt by Pharao, that he might be glorified in Pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rao, and make his name clere in all the worlde.<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.</note> So of the manne borne blynde from his natiuytie, nother this man hath ſynned nor his parentes, but that the workes of god moughte be manyfeſte in hym. And when god doth afflicte his people for theyr ſynnes, he dothe not therfore afflycte them, that by theyr afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, they ſhuld ſatisfie for theyr ſynnes. For the paſſion and ſufferynge of Ieſus Chriſte only, is the raunſome and expiation of our ſynnes. But ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he afflicteth, that by affliction he maye dryue ſynners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce. For repentaunce or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance cometh fyrſte by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege
<pb facs="tcp:10370:20"/> of ſynne: and then by faythe, that our ſynne is forgyuen vs for goddes promiſe ſake: and of faith burgeth forthe the callinge on the name of god.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶In tribulation we muſte praye. Cap. vii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HERE</hi> are we taughte, what a chryſten man muſte doo in temptation, whenne he ſeeth hym ſelfe forſaken of al men, that is, to praye, and not to ceaſſe to praye, but to praye in feyth, myſtruſting nothinge,<note place="margin">Ia. 1.</note> for he that myſtruſteth, is lyke the raige of the ſee, whiche is caried with the wynde, and toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and dryuen with vyolence. Whiche thinge alſo Chryſte war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs of,<note place="margin">Matt. 16.</note> ſayinge. Watche and praye, that ye entre not into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. So lyke wyſe Salomon: Sonne,<note place="margin">Eccle. 38.</note> in thy ſyckeneſſe deſpyſe
<pb facs="tcp:10370:20"/> not thy ſelfe, but pray to the lorde, and he ſhal heale the. Therto god hath alſo commaunded, that we ſhulde in tribulation call on hym: yea and calleth that inuocation or crying on hym, a ſacrifice, the true and mooſte accepted honour. For ſo ſaythe the pſalm.<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.</note> Call to me in the day of thy trouble. And he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth promyſes, And I wyll dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the, and thou ſhalt honour me And he ſayde before in the pſalm, that he regarded not the oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of beaſtes and ſuch other workes, but that he delyteth in this ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. if that we cal on hym in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and beleue, that he wyll helpe vs: and when we are holpen, to gyue thankes, and preache his be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefyte. And ſoo lyke wyſe he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the hope,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> wherby we tary his helpe in affliction, ſacrifice. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb facs="tcp:10370:21"/> you the ſacrifice of iuſtice, and hope ye in the lord. as though he ſhulde ſay, that hope is a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, wherby we yelde iuſtyce to god, that (ſeinge he hath ſoo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed) he wyl plucke vs out, and delyuer vs: for ſoo moche he is ryghtuouſe and true. Thou ſeeſt then, that chriſtian pacience hath euer hope annexed: but that hope beholdeth no creatures, but onely the word and promyſe of god, and holdeth hope agaynſte hope, as ſayth Paule: that is when al cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures fayle, and ſhewe no helpe at all, yet is there hope, that god wyll helpe. And thoughe he gyue vs not thoſe thynges, whiche we wolde, or by that waye or meanes that we wyll, yet gouerneth he ſo the ende, throughe his wyſedome and goodneſſe, that we peryſſhe
<pb facs="tcp:10370:21"/> not, and that our prayers be not ſpente in vayne. Paule teacheth the ſame in this gradation. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation bryngeth pacience, when he commeth thither, and teacheth vs, that we ought to holde a ſure hope in tyme of trouble, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a promyſe.<note place="margin">Roma. 4.</note> Hope maketh vs neuer a ſhamed. We muſte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beleue, that we are harde of god, that god wyll helpe vs, and that we are defended of god. For ſo the pſalmes commaunde vs to beleue and praye.<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.</note> And in my trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble haue I cried to the lorde, and to my god haue I called, and he hath graciouſely frome his holye temple harde my voyce.<note place="margin">Pſal. 80.</note> In trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thou haſt called on me, and I haue delyuered the, I haue gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly herde the, in the darkenes of trouble. He hath cryed to me,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10370:22"/> and I wyll here hym. I am with hym in trouble, I wyll delyuer hym, and he ſhall glorifie me. Of this matter we haue noo fewe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>examples. Chyldren prayed in the myddes of the fornace, and they were harde and delyuered.<note place="margin">Danie. 3.</note> Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el in the myddes of captiuitie, prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, and in the den of lions, and he was preſerued.<note place="margin">Daniel. 9.</note> Suſan forſaken of all men, prayed, and ſhe was harde.<note place="margin">Ionas. 2. Eſai. 38.</note> Ionas in the bealy of the fyſhe, prayed. Hezechias ſyckened euen to the deathe, he tourned his face to the wall, and prayed to the lorde, and the lord harde hym, and was made hole.<note place="margin">4. Re. 20. Luc. 22.</note> Chriſt in the time of his tribulation and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſheding forth dropes of bloud. Stephan in the myddes of theym that ſtoned hym,<note place="margin">Act. 7.</note> prayed. Whyle Peter was kepte in pryſon,<note place="margin">Act. 12.</note> there
<pb facs="tcp:10370:22"/> was prayer made of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation for hym. Suche examples oughte to ſtyrre vp our myndes and our faythe, to praye more dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, and with a more feruent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. For affliction, and the great waylynges and ſorowe of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flycted, are regarded of god, ſoo moche, that noo more acceptable ſacrifice can be offered to god, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if ye offer a contrite and an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble harte, whiche god neuer refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, as ſayth the prophete.<note place="margin">Pſal. 112.</note> Who is lyke the lorde our god, whiche dwelleth in the hyghe, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth and beholdeth lowe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? Whom ſhall I loke on,<note place="margin">Eſai. 66.</note> but on the poore and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trite in ſpirite, and hym that feareth my worde. The lorde is nyghe them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.</note> whiche haue a troubled harte. We are taught alſo, that the lorde behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:10370:23"/> and hereth the prayers and crye of ſynners, of thoſe ſynners, whiche althoughe they haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted neuer ſo filthy offences, yet beleue that the lorde god is theyr god, for his promyſe made to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham: that is, whiche beleue, that they haue god the father pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified in heauen for Ieſus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake. and through this fayth call to god, and are hard: through this faythe, theyr ſynnes commyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ar waſhed away. And the prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er of the afflycted gothe throughe to the trone of the grace of god. This faythe is moche worthe, to perſwade the hart of the afflycted in temptation, that his prayer is harde. And for as moche as god is more redier to here, then we to praye, we ought ſurely to beleue, that our prayers are not ydel, but
<pb facs="tcp:10370:23"/> that they pleaſe god, and are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly harde, as Sirach alſo doth warne vs:<note place="margin">Eccle. 18.</note> Before thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, prepare thy ſoule, and be not, as a man that tempteth god, that is, lyfte vp thy mynde with a ſure confidence, that god wyl here the, but not for thy worthyneſſe: But fyrſte, bycauſe thou arte ſure, that god hath commanded vs to pray, and for bycauſe god hath promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed graciouſly to here vs. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for bycauſe thou haſte a forme and maner of prayer aſſygned of hym. Wherfore we nede not to feare, that our prayer ſhuld offend hym, for god caſteth of no manne that commeth vnto hym, yea he calleth all men vnto hym, whiche are troubled in hart:<note place="margin">Matth. 11.</note> Come to me all ye that labour and are laden, and I ſhall refreſſhe you. Mary
<pb facs="tcp:10370:24"/> Magdalyn was a ſynner, whiche afterwarde ſhe beganne to waſhe Chriſtes fete with her teares, ſhe harde of Chryſte.<note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note> Thy ſynnes are forgiuen the. Alſo the thefe, in his extreme ſufferynge, went to ioye. Lyke wyſe of zach. Matth. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.<note place="margin">Matth. 9.</note> For he came not to calle the ryghtuouſe, but ſynners. He came to ſeke the loſte ſhepe, and loſte dram or grote.<note place="margin">Luc. 18.</note> He hath promyſed to them that repente, remiſſion of ſynnes, and receyueth them in to his fauour, as the prodigal ſonne. If we confeſſe our ſynnes, he is feythefull and ryghtuouſe to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue vs our ſynnes,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.</note> and to clenſe vs from al iniquitie.<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note> I haue ſaid, I wyll confeſſe agaynſte my ſelfe, my vnryghtuouſenes, and thou haſte forgyuen the wyckednes of my ſynne. Alſo if the wycked ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:10370:24"/> repent from all his ſynnes,<note place="margin">Ezech. 18.</note> which he hath done, and ſhall kepe al my preceptes, and wyll kepe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and iuſtice, he ſhal lyue, and ſhall not dye.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Of prayer and the maner of prayer in tribulation.</head>
                  <p>¶<hi>PRAYER</hi> is the deſyre of the harte for any thynge, to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of god, it is the penſyfe ſyghe of godlye myndes, whiche calle on the name of the lorde. We are commaunded to praye:<note place="margin">Matt. 16. 1. Teſ. 5. Colo. 4.</note> watch and pray. Alſo, Aſke and ye ſhal haue. Aſke and it ſhal be gyuen you. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, Praye contynually. Agayne: Be buſy in prayer, and watche in it.<note place="margin">Luc. 18.</note> For god dothe not onely ſuffer vs to praye, but alſo commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, as he hath commaunded vs, not to kyll, not to committe adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery. Wherfore lyke as they ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:25"/> that kyll, or robbe, euen ſo do they that neuer praye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Whoſe preyars are hard of god.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Eccle. 9.</note>¶<hi>THE</hi> deſyre of the pore, god he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. The praier of him that meke neth him ſelfe, penetrateth &amp; goth throughe the cloudes.<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.</note> He hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded the praier of the meke, and hath not deſpyſed theyr prayers. The lorde is nyghe all them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 144. Ioh. 4.</note> that crye vnto hym in truthe. Suche worſhyppers god requireth, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che worſhyp hym in ſpiryte.<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> The ryghtuouſe haue cryed, and the lorde hath hard them, and he hath delyuered them from al theyr tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.<note place="margin">Pſal. 60.</note> From the endes of the worlde haue I called to the, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my hart was dyſmaied, and in a rocke haſt thou exalted me.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> To the lord haue I cried in my trouble, and he hath graciouſey harde me.<note place="margin">Eſai. 66.</note> He behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:10370:25"/> the lowly and broken in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and ſuche as feare his worde. Partes of trewe prayer, are the promyſe, faythe, the affecte, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre in the name of Chryſte, and thankes gyuynge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶The promyſe of god.</head>
                  <p>¶<hi>VVHAT</hi> ſo euer ye aſke the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my name,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> he ſhall gyue it you.<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.</note> Crye on me in the day of thy trybulation, and I wyll delyuer the, and thou ſhalte gloryfie me. He ſhall gyue good thynges to them that aſke hym.<note place="margin">Matth. 11. Marc. 11.</note> I ſaye vnto you, what ſo euer thynges ye aſke in your prayer, beleue that ye ſhal receyue, and they ſhal happen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. Aſke, and it ſhall be giuen you.<note place="margin">Matt. 18.</note> If that two of you agree of any thynge vpon the erthe, what ſo euer thynge they ſhall requyre, it ſhalbe giuen them of my father,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:26"/> which is in heuen.<note place="margin">Hiere. 33.</note> Call to me, and I wyll gracyouſely here the. In prayer, goddes promyſe muſte be conſydered, howe god hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed, that he wyll here vs. For he whiche hath commaunded to praye, hath promyſed that he wyl bothe here vs and helpe vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Faythe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ia. 1. 1. Ioh. 5.</note>¶<hi>VVE</hi> muſte praye with a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, doubtyng nothynge. This is the confidence, whiche we haue towarde hym, that what ſoo euer we deſyre, accordynge to his wyll, he hereth vs. A prayer withoute fayth obteyneth nothinge at god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des hand. We muſt therfore pray in faythe. And if we aſke in fayth, he hereth vs. Fayth is aſſuredlye to beleue, that god forgyueth vs our ſynnes, for Chriſtes ſake, and not only forgiueth our ſinnes, but
<pb facs="tcp:10370:26"/> alſo is preſent with vs, ruleth and gouerneth vs, that he maye make vs ſafe. In this faythe if we aſke any thynge, god dothe graciouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here vs. For god wyll gyue all thinges to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleue in him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶To aſke in the name of Ieſu,</head>
                  <p>¶<hi>IS</hi> to haue a reſpect, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and wyll of god, that the name of god maye be glorifyed. For the ende of euery prayer, is the glory of god. To aſke therfore in the name of Ieſu, is to aſke and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre the glory of Chryſte, and the ſpredynge abrode of his name.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶The affecte to deſire any thinge.</head>
                  <p>¶<hi>THE</hi> lordes prayer teacheth playnely, what thynge we ſhulde praye for. More ouer, fayth, hope, loue, pacience. We muſt alſo pray, that we be not tempted, for prayer onely obteyneth the victory of all
<pb facs="tcp:10370:27"/> temptations. Alſo for publike and common neceſſities, for offycers, for peace.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Thankes gyuyng.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 49. Pſal. 115.</note>¶<hi>OFFER TO</hi> god, prayſe. To the ſhal I ſacrifice the hoſt or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of prayſe, and I ſhall calle on the name of the lorde.<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> I wyll bleſſe the lorde at all tymes, his prayſe ſhal euer be in my mouthe. None turned agayne,<note place="margin">Luc. 11.</note> to gyue glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to god, but the ſtraunger. The faythfull gyue thankes, that they ar delyuered of theyr trouble, they magnifie god, and preache forth, his gyuynge of benefy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es: but god oftentymes deferreth to here, to exerciſe the faythe of the godly, as it apereth in Syropheniſſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Luc. 18. and yet ſtynte not they to praye,<note place="margin">Luc. 18.</note> nor myſtruſte god, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe they obteyne not ſtreight
<pb facs="tcp:10370:27"/> wayes, that whiche they aſke and deſyre, but continue ſtyll in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. For continuance in praier hath the rewarde.<note place="margin">Daniel. 9.</note> He continued in prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, he praied the hole day through euen to euentyde, and was viſited of Gabriell. We muſt preſcrybe or appoynte no tyme to god.<note place="margin">Iudith. 9.</note> He that continueth knockynge, to hym it ſhall be opened. God gaue not to Abraham ſtreyghte wayes, that which he promiſed. Therfore muſt we ſaye, If thou wylte lorde,<note place="margin">Marc. 1. Iob. 13.</note> thy wyll be fulfylled. Althoughe he ſhall kyll me, yet ſhall I truſte in hym.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶We oughte to be pacient in affliction, not to be angry, nor to ſpeake yuell of god. Cap. viii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PACIENCE,</hi> is to feele and conſider, that god doth ſcorge
<pb facs="tcp:10370:28"/> vs, to call vs to repentaunce, and therfore gladly to ſuffer the hand of god, and to haue a confidence, that god wyl forgiue vs, and that he wyll delyuer vs. Of this paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to godward, ſpryngeth forth pacience towarde men. For when the harte is at peace with god, it tarieth helpe of hym, and vtterly ſetteth aſide luſt to auenge. Thus pacience can neuer be, but when by fayth we are aſſured, that we pleaſe god, and that at lengthe it ſhall come to paſſe, that we ſhalbe ſaued. Chriſten pacience therfore, is the comfort and ioye of the hart in afflyctions, to whome there is annexed hope. For faythe preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiueth reconciliation and for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyuenes of ſynne, &amp; a promyſe of the ende. Hope taryeth and loketh for the ende to come, as ſayth Eſai
<pb facs="tcp:10370:28"/> In ſilence and hope ſhall be your ſtrengthe.<note place="margin">Eſai. 20.</note> For Hope hath his eye to the wyll of god, and knoweth, that god hath care on hym. And it ſhall come to paſſe, that god wyll gouerne the endes accordynge to his promyſe, althoughe there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere no helpe at all, in any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as it is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Abraham. Agaynſte all hope, he beleued in hope. that is, althoughe in the hole compaſſe of nature, there be no hope at al, yet beholdynge the worde of god, felte inwardly, that that whiche god hadde promyſed, ſhoulde come to paſſe. Who (as ſaythe Paule) calleth thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche are not, as thoughe they were? Therfore the mynd is quiete in chriſten pacience. For it conſydereth, that afflyctions are not yll, nor are layed on vs of god
<pb facs="tcp:10370:29"/> to our deſtruction. For he is well aſſured, that he is temted through the good wyll of god, and exercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to repentaunce for his helthe. And for as moche as the mynd is fyxed towarde this wyl of god, he is not angrye with god. For he knoweth, howe this calamitie or trouble commeth not by chaunce or fortune without a cauſe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther reioyſeth in affliction. that is it that Eſai ſpeaketh. In ſilence and hope ſhall be your ſtrengthe. that is, be ye not angry in god or with god.<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.</note> Be ye angry, but ſynne not, that is. Be ye not angry with god, bicauſe he ſuffereth you to be punyſhed, and doth not by and by helpe you, be ye not for that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, to exercyſe vengaunce, or to forſake god: but ſpeake cloſely within your hartes, that is, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:10370:29"/> the word, and accordyng ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſuffer affliction. Suche pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience is ſtedfaſte and ſure, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen when al mannes comfort and councell forſake vs. whiche thing holye ſcripture euidently proueth euery where. for he wyl not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull of the poore continually. The pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the poore ſhall not peryſhe at length. Tary the lorde,<note place="margin">Pſal. 26.</note> do manfully, comforte thy harte, and ſuffer the lord.<note place="margin">Eſai. 30.</note> In ſilence and hope, ſhall be thy ſtrengthe.<note place="margin">Thren. 3.</note> It is good to loke for the helthe of the lorde in ſilence.<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.</note> What ſoo euer is layde on the, receyue it, and when thou arte brought lowe, haue pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience. He that is pacient,<note place="margin">Prou. 14.</note> is ruled with moche wyſedome. He that is impatient, ſheweth forthe his fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhenes. In your pacience ſhall ye poceſſe your ſoules.<note place="margin">Matt. 10. Roma. 5.</note> Afflyction
<pb facs="tcp:10370:30"/> bringeth forthe pacience, pacience probation or triall, probatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hope, and hope ſhall neuer be a ſhamed. So Dauid,<note place="margin">2. Re. 16.</note> paciently ſuffered the perſecution of his ſonne, and the curſe of Semei. Iob is a notable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of pacience. The lord gaue the lorde hath taken away. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham was pacient,<note place="margin">Gen. 12.</note> when his wyfe was taken away, and ſet in Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raos houſe. Chryſte is the onely captayne and moſte perfecte exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of pacience. So farre is it of, that aduerſities ſhuld noy or hurt vs, that they are very profytable vnto vs. For the good, the more they ar afflycted, the more pacient they are, knowynge that through moche trouble, is the way of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. for they knowe, that by moch pacience, they ar tried and proued as Peter ſayth.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> wherby the triall
<pb facs="tcp:10370:30"/> of our faythe, maye be more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſe then golde, whiche pery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth and is tried by fier. wherfore a proffe or triall helpeth to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of hope. For when we conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, that in no ſuche ſo great affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we are not forſaken, we ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confidently, that neuer after this ſhal we be forſaken. we ought therfore pacientely to ſuffer thoſe ylles, which happen on vs in this worlde. for if we be impacient, we be not chriſtians. For as many as haue ben ſythen the begynnynge of the worlde hytherto, godly and chriſtian men, they haue al ben af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flycted with manyfolde troubles. But forbycauſe, they haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with pacience, their hope ſet and fyxed in god, therfore they ar made ſafe, as witneſſeth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the holy, from the fyrſte
<pb facs="tcp:10370:31"/> Abel, vnto thoſe ryghtuouſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in theſe days ar on lyue. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it behoued euen Chryſte hym ſelf, by the croſſe, to entre into life. And this in all aduerſities is gret comforte, and of great ſtrength, to knowe, that god requireth paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and that myngled with ioy. But mans reaſon perceyueth not that,<note place="margin">Colo. 1.</note> but god teacheth it. For our reaſon is therfore troubled &amp; vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in perſecution, bycauſe it thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, that we ar afflycted, bycauſe god other hateth vs, or dothe not regarde vs, nother wyl helpe vs. Theſe falſe opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s god plucketh from vs, and teacheth vs, that we ar afflycted, not bycauſe he hateth vs, but bycauſe he wyll other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende vs, or when we be amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſo to continue, accordynge to that ſayinge: He correcteth the
<pb facs="tcp:10370:31"/> ſonne whom he loueth. Agayn: I wyl not the deathe of a ſynner.<note place="margin">Ezech. 18.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, He hath concluded all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſynne, not to dyſtroye all, but to haue mercye on all. And this thynge engendereth gladnes in our myndes, to knowe and fele, that it pleaſeth god, to haue vs afflycted. For we muſt be lyke the ymage of his ſonne. More ouer, that in our affliction he wyl helpe vs, and kepe vs, and alſo comfort vs with the holy goſt, and ſet our conſcience at peace, and make vs be gladde in god, ſo that we deſire helpe of hym. For he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that we ſhulde loke for helpe at his hande, accordynge to this: All they that tarye the,<note place="margin">Eſai. 49.</note> ſhal not be confounded. And god commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth lykewyſe, that we ſhuld aſke helpe of hym. Call on me in the
<pb facs="tcp:10370:32"/> daye of trouble, and I wyll dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the, and thou ſhalte gloryfie me. Of this pacience and comfort god alonely is the auctour, which alſo giueth pacience.<note place="margin">Pſal. 70. Pſal. 61. Hiere. 29.</note> For thou art my pacience o lord. yet o my ſoule be vnder and ſubiecte to god. for of hym is my pacience. Thynke the thoughtes of peace, that I maye gyue you the ende and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> The god of pacience and comforte. &amp;c. This chriſtian paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath certayne condycions, wherby it is knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be the true pacience. Fyrſte it grudgeth not, nother excuſeth it ſelfe, as though it ſhulde ſuffer vnworthily for his ſynnes. wherfore he ſitteth downe and holdeth his peace, as Hiere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie ſaythe.<note place="margin">Thren. 3.</note> He ſytteth alone, and ſpeketh no worde, for he hath laid a yocke vpon hym. Secondely it
<pb facs="tcp:10370:32"/> caſteth all carefulnes on god,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note> and committeth it ſelfe al hole to god, that goddes wyl be done, and not his. Thyrdely, it humbleth hym ſelfe, and caſteth of ryotte, and the pleaſure of the worlde. Fourthly, he is mery and redye to ſuffer yet more heuyer and more greuouſe ylles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Socour in affliction muſte be aſked of god. Capi. ix.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVE MVSTE</hi> loke for helpe in al afflyctions, for god pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſeth his helpe, ſayenge. I am with you, feare ye not, I wyll ſtrengthe you. Agayne,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> Without me, ye are able to doo nothynge. But when he is preſente, we are able to doo all thynges throughe hym. And if he be with vs,<note place="margin">Roma. 8.</note> who ſhall be agaynſte vs? Of what
<pb facs="tcp:10370:33"/> daunger ſhall we be aferde of? he hath promyſed trewely to be with vs, vntyll the ende of the worlde, and vndoubtedly he wyll be. Let vs cal therfore on his helpe, he is trewe, and is redy to al them that call on hym in truthe.<note place="margin">Iudit. 6.</note> Iudith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrynge helpe of god, ſayd: Helpe me thy handemaiden,<note place="margin">Heſt. 14.</note> which haue none other helpe but the lorde. Giue vs helpe from the holy place or elles,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> he ſendeth helpe from his holy place. and from Sion wil he defende the.<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.</note> O god gyue hede to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde my helpe, and haſt to helpe me o lorde. Bleſſed is that man, whoſe helpe is of the.<note place="margin">Pſal. 83. Pſal. 107.</note> Helpe vs from tribulation. For vayn is the helthe of man.<note place="margin">Pſal. 120.</note> My helpe is of the lorde, whiche made heauen and erthe. In tyme of tribulation we oughte from aboue to loke for the
<pb facs="tcp:10370:33"/> helpe of god: but the maner, tyme, and kynde of helpe is vnknowen vnto vs, that fayth and hope may haue place, which ſticketh to thoſe thynges, whiche are not ſene nor harde. Do not therfore in tyme of trouble runne without thy ſelfe, but tary within thy ſelfe, and tary the ſtrength of the lorde: He wyll come, if thou departe not: he wyl ſtrengthe the, if thou ſeke none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrengthe. For he commeth not to them that flee, but to them that tarye boldelye. Tribulation muſt not be ouercome with flight, but with conſtancye, and ſtycking in the faythe of the name of god. Alſo the helpe of the lorde is ouer them, that onely put theyr confy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and truſte in god: he is redy with all his angelles, when al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges forſake theym: he hath
<pb facs="tcp:10370:34"/> a reſpect to his in afflyction conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually. He kepeth them, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth them.<note place="margin">3. Re. 17.</note> To Helias when he was fled and was hungry, he ſent a raue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which brought him bread. Agayne,<note place="margin">2. Re. 19.</note> he ſente hym bread &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by his aungell. He was with the elder Tobie,<note place="margin">Tobi. 5. Heſt. 9.</note> and at length he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led hym of his blyndenes. He tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the waylinge of the Iewes in to ioye.<note place="margin">Iudit. 10.</note> He wrought meruaylouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Betulians, which cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon hym.<note place="margin">Daniel. 5.</note> He was with Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel and the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the fornace of fier, that the fier ſhuld not hurt them.<note place="margin">Dani. 14.</note> When Daniell was in the den of lyons in Chaldee, the lorde ſent hym his dynner from Ieury. Suſan was lefte comfortles and in deſperation, and yet in extreme daunger, god delyuered her, and conſidered her anguyſhe.<note place="margin">Ionas. 2.</note> He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued
<pb facs="tcp:10370:34"/> Ionas in the bealy of the fyſhe, that he ſhulde not peryſhe, which yet had deſerued death. He was with Peter in priſon, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered hym.<note place="margin">Act. 12.23</note> He broughte Paule forthe of pryſon, to whome god ſpake by a viſyon in the nyghte. Feare not, but ſpeake, and holde not thy peace. And for as moche as I am with the, noo man ſhall drawe nyghe to hurte the. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Paule cryeth on this maner: As the paſſions and ſufferynges of Chriſt do habounde in vs,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> euen ſo do conſolations and comforte by Chriſte. We muſt therfore aſke helpe in tyme of trouble, of god onely: whiche of hym ſelfe, and by hym ſelfe, defendeth euerye man, that is his, and not by the helpe of man. Of whiche thyng there be examples, howe ofte tymes he
<pb facs="tcp:10370:35"/> holpe the people of Iſraell, when none of all the people about them were with them, but all agaynſte them, alonely with his preſence, throughe his trewe worſhyppe in Hieruſalem &amp; Sion.<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> He will ſend helpe vnto the fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his holy place, and out of Sion ſhall he defende the. And as often as they loked not for helpe out of Sion, but out of Egypt, or from the Aſſirians, ſo oftentymes they fell, and were worſe hurte, as men whiche claue to a ſtaffe of a rede. For helpe or ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cour required of creatures, is not onelye vayne, but is alſo to our hurte and loſſe, as Luke telleth, of the woman, whiche hadde the courſe of bloud, whiche beſtowed in vayne all the ſubſtance ſhe had on phiſitions, and receyued helthe by fayth onely in Chryſt. For god
<pb facs="tcp:10370:35"/> deliuereth when moſt nede is, that his glory maye ſhyne the brygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Therfore the wyl of god muſt be loked on, and our helpe &amp; hope maye be affyxed in nothynge els, then in god, whiche is an helper in tyme conuenient: Whiche hath fyxed his eyes vpon the.<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note> For the eyes of the lorde are on the rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſe, and his eares redy to their prayers.<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> We may put no affiance nor truſte in man, nor in mannes helpe, but in god onely.<note place="margin">Pſal. 59.</note> Vayne is the helthe of menne. Curſed is he that truſteth in man,<note place="margin">Hiere. 17.</note> and maketh fleſſhe his defence, and his harte departed from god.<note place="margin">Deut. 17. Eſai. 31.</note> Thy kynge ſhall not increaſe his horſes. Wo to them whiche go downe into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, hopynge in the helpe of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Some in horſes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> and ſome in chariottes, but we in the name of
<pb facs="tcp:10370:36"/> the lorde.<note place="margin">Pſal. 146.</note> Nor hath he delyte in the ſtrengthe of the horſe, nother yet pleaſure in the legges of men. The lorde delyteth in theym that feare hym, and in them that putte theyr hope in hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Yet in afflyction or ſyckenes, medicyne and councell are not to be deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed. Cap. x.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOR GOD</hi> by inſtrumentes performeth his wyll, and doth and worketh all thynges in theyr order by meanes, as clerely teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth holy ſcripture.<note place="margin">Eſai. 38.</note> Eſai comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to take a cluſter of fygges, &amp; to playſter them vppon Ezechias wounde, and ſo to be made hole. This is certaynely a great prayſe and defence to phyſicke.<note place="margin">4. Re. 20. 2. Par. 32.</note> For god wil not the vſe of his creatures to be neglected or dyſpyſed. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth
<pb facs="tcp:10370:36"/> onely the faythe and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in creatures. And although he mought eaſyly haue healed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechias, with one worde: yet wold he doo it by medycine. Soo he mought bringe forth and increace chyldren of mannes body, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe or by ſome other maner, but yet he wyll do it by the womanne. Wherfore let vs vſe thynges, as god hath created them, with than<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes gyuyng, and let vs onely put no confidence in them: as we rede that Aſa dyd,<note place="margin">2. Co. 15.</note> whiche in his ſycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſought not the lorde, but phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. Hope muſt chiefely be put in the lorde, and afterwarde lette vs vſe the helpe of phyſitions, as the benefytte of god. Moreouer, we muſte conſider, that god hath created medycine, as wytneſſeth Ieſus Syrach:<note place="margin">Sirach. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Honour the phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb facs="tcp:10370:37"/> for neceſſyties ſake, for the hygheſt hath created hym. For of god is al remedy. &amp;c. Beſyde that, amonge the people of god, there were euer phyſitions, and Luke hym ſelfe the euangeliſte was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a phiſition.<note place="margin">Colo. 4.</note> But yet (as I ſaid) we muſte put no confidence in the phiſition, but rather in god. For phiſike without the workynge of god, helpeth nothynge, as wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the hiſtorie of the woman,<note place="margin">Matth. 9.</note> whiche twelue yeres ſuffered the fluxe. For the outwarde phiſike is deceytfull, and nothyng at all, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte helthe be inwardely gyuen of god. The woman is not repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, bycauſe ſhe ſpente moche on phyſitions, but rather is priuyly ſhewed, that phyſycke is vayne, when it is attemted without god. So maye we not deſpiſe phiſicke,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:37"/> whom the hygheſt hath created of the erthe: ſo that we renounce our wyll into the hande of god, which is the chiefe poynt, that is by phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, other to heale vs, or to kyll vs. This is the ſtronge faythe in god, throughe which, no ſickenes is ſo greuous and vncurable, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is not made hole. This faythe I ſaye, is nothynge elles, but the moſt lyuely opinion and vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted truſt in the mercy of god, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by a man vndoutedly perſwadeth hym ſelfe, that he is in the fauour of god, and that god is courteyſe and forgyuynge hym al thynges, that he hath other doone or ſayde. Courteyſe, in good thinges: forgi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge, in yl thynges.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> This faith commeth by herynge, and hering by the word of god. Phiſicke ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore may not be deſpiſed. For god
<pb facs="tcp:10370:38"/> is the aucthor and creator of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, in whiche alſo he worketh as by a meane. Soo Helizeus toke ſalte and caſte it into the fountain of waters, whiche were verye yll, and vnholſome, and made the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters hole. Agayne. He purged and ryd the lepre of Naaman,<note place="margin">4. Re. 2.</note> captain vnder the kynge of Syria, in the water of Iordan.<note place="margin">4. Re. 5.</note> Water without the worde and promyſe of god, is nothyng. as if any other had waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed hym ſelfe a hundred times in Iordan, he ſhulde not haue bene clenſed. Naaman is clenſed, for he had a promyſe. Be thou waſſhed, and thou ſhalt be hole. When he regardeth not this promyſe, but onely the water, he erreth, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryeth in leproſye, and ſo ſhoulde haue periſhed, and haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer agaynſte god, oneleſſe he
<pb facs="tcp:10370:38"/> had ben warned of his ſeruantes. He came therfore with faythe, and was made hole.<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.</note> Soo Chryſte to make the blynde man hole, made clay with ſpyttell. Agayne.<note place="margin">Matth. 9.</note> The hem of chriſtes garment touched, delyuered the woman frome the fluxe of bloud. The voice of Chriſt called forthe Lazarus. The voyce of Chriſt called forth vncleane ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rites from men. The ſhadowe of Peter expelleth ſyckenes. So mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che can the creature do, taken into the handes of the almyghty, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath not this ſtrengthe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but of the euerlaſtyng word of god. of whome it receyueth the ſtrength of doinge, that it reſteth not, but is euer workynge and myghtye. For there is nothynge made of god in vayne, althoughe it be neuer ſoo vyle. For therfore
<pb facs="tcp:10370:39"/> god created thoſe vile thynges, to ſignifie, that he him ſelfe worketh in thoſe abiecte and vyle thinges: but the wycked doo attrybute the ſtrengthe of curynge, healynge, multiplieng, and bringyng forth, to the erthe, nature, and herbes: but the faythefull attribute it, to the lyuynge worde of god, and to the preſent power of god. For god worketh all thynges, by the erthe, herbes, and other his creatures, as by inſtrumentes: but yet we ought not to attribute thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to trees &amp; herbes, althoughe god vſe thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges for our ſake, but to god, which worketh al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, in all thynges, that all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges maye be referred to theyr firſt well ſprynge. Wherfore it is ſure, that god by inſtrumentes dothe worke, clenſe, heale, and make
<pb facs="tcp:10370:39"/> ſafe. So god only fedeth vs,<note place="margin">Matt. 6.</note> your heauenly father fedeth them, yet vſeth he bread as an inſtrument to fede by.<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.</note> Bread confyrmeth the harte of man. Agayn. God alone kepeth vs and defendeth vs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to this.<note place="margin">Pſal. 227.</note> Except the lorde do kepe the citie, he that kepeth it, watcheth in vayne, and yet he ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth it, with the myniſtery of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles and gouernours. Fynally, god is the auctour and lorde of al thynges, he hath his organes and inſtrumentes, with the which, as with meanes he doth what he wil.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>¶In afflyction no tyme may be appoynted to god, nother yet maner wherby we wolde be delyuered. Ca. xi.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THERE IS</hi> no time nor mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of afflyction, to be preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crybed or lymytted to the lord, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:10370:40"/> he deffer the matter a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſeaſon, as it apereth in the .v. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter of Iohn,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> that the infirmitie of the ſycke was prolonged vntyl the .xxxviii. yere, by the wyll of god, vntyll Chryſte ſhulde come and be glorified. So let vs beleue certaynly, all our afflictions to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the longer, throughe the myghtye wyll and worke of god, that at the laſte the lorde be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in vs.<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.</note> A certayne manne was borne blynde, and dyd continue ſo blynde vntyll he came to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect aege of a man. but wherfore? Veryly, that the worke of the lord myght be ſhewed in hym. In like wyſe the Iſraelytes were not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greuouſelye punyſſhed vnder Pharao in Egypt, but alſo a long ſeaſon, not that they ſhulde be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, but rather that the name
<pb facs="tcp:10370:40"/> of the lorde ſhulde be glorified in them. Iob alſo was caſt into gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſe hel paynes many monthes, that by the continuaunce of his peynes, it myght be made many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſte, that all men were lyers, and god onely trewe. that is, that the name of god by hym myghte be glorified. In lyke maner Ioſeph, hauynge knowlege by his dreme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhulde be a gouernour, was kepte longe tyme, partely vnder greuouſe ſeruitude and bondage, and partely in priſon. but for none other cauſe, but that the name of god, by hym delyuered from ſoo lowe humilitie, and broughte to ſo great honour, myght be glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. God wyl therfore helpe when nede ſhall require, whenne we be compelled to deſpeyre in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne helpe, and when all carnal
<pb facs="tcp:10370:41"/> councell ſhall deceyue vs, for god onely wyll be gloryfied.<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.</note> Chryſte dyd not chaunge water into wyne at the begynnynge, but dyd tarye vntyll it appered manyfeſtly to al the geſtes, that there lacked wine. that the glory onely to god and to none other myght be gyuen. It ſemeth oftentymes, that god doth leaue his elect in the middel of all yll, but ſodeynely he helpeth and gyueth ſocour, ſpecially when all thynge is broughte to deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and beſyde al hope, with ſome rare and ſeldome ſhewen myracle he helpeth, althoughe natural re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy do lacke, and trouble abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d on euery ſyde, ſoo that it ſemeth, that the lorde hath forgotten his elect: but afterwarde he fayleth not to deliuer them out of the mid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of al theyr troubles more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſely.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:41"/> He myght haue let Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao, that he ſhuld not haue puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the chyldren of Iſraell, but when all mans helpe was paſt, he delyuered his people from Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao in the red ſee. The lorde dothe prolong helpe for our vtilitie and profyte, that he myghte exercyſe and proue faythe by temptation: ſo that he onely might poſſeſſe the title and name of a helper, that we myght lerne the better to truſte in god, and to haue compaſſion vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon other that be tempted. as in the pſalm.<note place="margin">Pſal, 17.</note> And thy lernynge hath corrected me for euer, and thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplyne ſhal teache me.<note place="margin">Hebre. 2.</note> So Paule ſpeaketh of Chryſte: It behoueth that Chriſte, in all thynges ſhuld be made lyke his brethern, that he myghte be mercyfull ouer theym. We ought not therfore to deſpeire
<pb facs="tcp:10370:42"/> in the tyme of afflyction, ſpecially when we knowe certaynely, that the terme and ende of puniſhment and payne, is to be preſcribed, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and appoynted of god, as the prophetes beare witnes. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the yeres beginne to be fullfylled,<note place="margin">Hiere. 29.</note> I wyl viſet you, and rayſe vppon you a good worde.<note place="margin">Hiere. 30.</note> Alſo, and the daye ſhall be, that I wyll breake his yoke from thy necke, and ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſhal beare no more rule ouer it.<note place="margin">Eſai. 28. Abac. 2.</note> He whiche ſhall beleue, ſhall make noo haſte. He whiche yet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a farre of, ſhall appere at the ende, and ſhall not lye, althoughe he tary, yet loke for hym, for he is commynge, and at the laſt he ſhal come, and ſhal not be ſlowe. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſte ſaye:<note place="margin">Matt. 6. Marc. 1.</note> The wyll of the lorde be fulfylled. Alſo, Lord, if thou wylte, thou mayſte make
<pb facs="tcp:10370:42"/> me cleane. Alſo Paule ſayth.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> The lorde is faythefull, whiche wyll not ſuffer you to be temted aboue your myght, but ſhall gyue with temptation power to reſyſte, that you maye be able to ſuffer.<note place="margin">Iob. 13.</note> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe he kyl me, yet I wil truſt in hym.<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.</note> If I ſhall walke in the myddell of the ſhadowe of death, I wyll not feare euyl thynges, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou arte with me. Iudith in the .vii. and .viii. chapiter, is a good exaumple. The people of Iſraell were forty yeres in deſert. God dydde not gyue to Abraham ſhortely that whiche he promyſed. So Chryſte ſayde his houre was not yet come.<note place="margin">Ioh. 2. Matt. 14. Matth. 4.</note> The womanne of Chananie is a good example. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Chryſt was tempted of the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell in wyldernes forty dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10370:43"/>
               <head>¶It is a great comfort to them that be in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, to remembre, that Chriſte was alſo tempted and exerciſed with yll as we be wont to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed. Cap. xii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FYRST VVE</hi> ſe Chriſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: in whom we haue an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of pacience and longe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferynge. This is our captayne, whom we ought to folowe in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferynge, ne leſte it ſhulde be heuy to vs, when we be tempted and puniſhed in this worlde, other of the dyuell or of his membres. For as the apoſtell ſaythe.<note place="margin">Hebre. 5.</note> We haue a biſhop tempted in al thynges lyke to vs, without ſynne. And for as moche it choſeth him ſo to be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he myght the better helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be tempted, Therfore Chriſt was delyuered to the dyuell to be tempted, as he was after betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:10370:43"/> to the Iewes to be crucyfyed: that we, which be tempted, by him and in hym myght lyue. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, that by his temptation he ſhulde ouercome, leſte we ſhuld obey and be ouercome in tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and by that his deathe he myght redeme vs from perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all deathe. Therfore let vs not be angry, nor take it greuouſly, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we be let flyp by god our father in to diuers temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; afflyctions: Bycauſe no man is te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, excepte the lord wyl. nor the dyuel hath no power to hurte any man, excepte the lorde wyll per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte and ſuffer hym. And when ſo euer he ſhall ſuffer hym to te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, yet he wyl not ſuffer vs to be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboue our power. We haue not onely Chriſt for our example, but alſo the godly bothe prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:10370:44"/> and apoſtelles, whiche in lyke wyſe be tempted, perſecuted, ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.12.</note> kylled, &amp; crucified. as Paule of hym ſelfe wytneſſeth. It is a great comfort to the godly, when for the name of Chriſt and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goſpell, they ſuffer perſecution, impriſonment, &amp; at the laſt death, in whiche troubles yet ioye and afflyction haue place and be mixt to gether. If they be puniſſhed, it is ioye and comforte to theym, to haue Chryſt and al good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men felowes with them in their afflictions.<note place="margin">1. Teſ. 1.</note> as Paule ſaythe. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuynge the worde with greatte afflyction, and ioye of the holye goſte. So Chryſte dothe comfort his electe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> ſayinge: In the world you ſhall haue afflyction, but be of good comforte, I haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the worlde. You ſhall wepe
<pb facs="tcp:10370:44"/> and lament, and the worlde ſhall reioyce: you ſhall mourne, but your mournynge ſhal be tourned in to ioye.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15. Matt. 16.</note> The ſeruaunte is not better then the mayſter. He that wyll folowe me, let hym deny him ſelfe. &amp;c. He which dothe not take vp his croſſe and folowe. &amp;c.<note place="margin">Matt. 16. Marc. 8.</note> He that wyll ſaue his ſoule, ſhal loſe it. &amp;c. and he whiche wyll loſe his ſoule for my ſake, ſhall fynde it euerlaſtyngely. For the goſpell is the worde of the croſſe, who ſoo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer preacheth it trewely, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, muſte nedes ſuffer afflycti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For the goſpell dothe reproue the worlde, and condemneth thoſe thynges, whiche be in the worlde, but the worlde can not ſuffer that. Therfore he punyſheth, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and kylleth the godlye. We haue exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples inowe. Cayn killed
<pb facs="tcp:10370:45"/> Abell, Eſau perſecuted Iacob, Saul Dauid, Pharao Moyſen, the Phariſeis Chryſte, the Iewes the Apoſtelles, Herode Iohn the baptiſt. If therfore we be lykewiſe punyſhed, and tempted, there cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth no newe thynges to vs. But let vs remembre Chryſte and his apoſtels our examples, which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed and warned vs of ſuch thynges, which were in lyke wyſe puniſhed, &amp; dyd teache vs, that al ſuche as wold lyue godly &amp; meke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. Acto. 14.</note> ſhulde ſuffer perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And by many troubles we muſte entre into the kyngedome of god.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>¶It is great comfort in affliction that no man can hurte the faythfull, except Chryſte wyll. Cap. xiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALTHOVGHE</hi> the worlde and the dyuel be neuer ſo fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riouſe
<pb facs="tcp:10370:45"/> and madde, yet the faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full can not be hurte.<note place="margin">Pſal, 3.</note> I wyll not feare a thouſand people, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng me about, bicauſe they ſtand vnder the wynge of god. Alſo all the creatures canne not hurte the faythefull, except god wyll. The water did not hurt the Iſraelites: the fyre dyd not hurt the thre chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, beinge in the furnace: the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons dyd nothynge hurte Daniel: Dauid plucked a beare out of the mouthe of a lyon, as the epyſtel to the Hebrewes wrytten, clerely wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſeth. If the faythefull peryſſhe in battayle, it is the good wyll of god. whitout whoſe wyll and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feraunce, no aduerſytie can come vnto them. And he that hurteth one faythfull, doth not hurte him but god. For god dothe reuenge the wronge done to the faythfull,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:46"/> as it were done to hym ſelfe. And if any aduerſite or heuynes, hang ouer the people of god, god regar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth and taketh that euen as he hym ſelfe were puniſhed, and gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued: but the reuengynge therof, is to be lefte to god. For god ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hym ſelfe defender of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuers:<note place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> he dothe take theym, and caryeth them vpon his ſhulders. Therfore god hath charge ouer the godly, whether they liue or dy. nor he doth not leaue them in the middel of their trouble and croſſe, but then he is more nere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and can not forget his electe. He is the god of Abraham, Iſaac, and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,<note place="margin">Matth. 10.</note> where ſoo euer they be. So Chriſte, The heares of your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des be nombred.<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.</note> The Iewes dyd ſeke to kyll Chryſte, but his tyme was not then comen.<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> No man did
<pb facs="tcp:10370:46"/> ſet handes vpon him, bycauſe his houre was not yet comme.<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> They went aboute to take hym, but he dydde eſcape from the myddell of theyr handes. Notwithſtandyng the wycked do often ouercome the godlye, and god dothe ſuffer the wycked to preuayle agaynſte the good: but throughe that rod, the lorde doth call his to repentance, and teacheth theym in feare. So Cayn preuayled agaynſte Abell, the Sodomites agaynſte Loth, Eſau agaynſte Iacob. The Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtians often dydde ouercome the Iſraelytes, Abymelech ouercame Sichimites, Saul agaynſt Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Herode agaynſte Iohn, the Iewes ageynſt Chriſte, Acab and Ieſabel againſt Helia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Iewes ageynſt Stephin, the turke often ouercometh the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. In theſe
<pb facs="tcp:10370:47"/> examples it is greate comforte to the godly, whiche ſuffer wronge: to whom the lorde ſaythe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note> I wyll fixe mine eies ſtedfaſtly vpon the. That whiche was done in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, is done alſo euen vnto the ende of the worlde. ¶The wycked thynke, that they ouercome, when that they kyl, and caſte other into exyle, and thynke that the lorde dothe forſake them, when he dothe not delyuer theym from deathe and perſecution, by ſome vyſible myracle. Surelye, Chryſte was ſoo delyuered from deathe: and ſo all they, whiche do beleue in Chryſte, by Chriſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered from deathe. God wolde not graunt (if he dyd not certayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know) that of perſecution, and ſuche other ylles, whiche be wont to chaunce to his electe, greatteſt
<pb facs="tcp:10370:47"/> profyt to come vnto them. He ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth them to be caſt into pryſon, into ylles, and into death, that he maye declare therby, that he hath both power and wil to ſaue them. Suche diligent care hath the lord ouer the godly. God with all his angelles is redye, when all other thynges do forſake. Wherof the pſalm ſaythe, Bycauſe my father and mother haue forſaken me, the lorde hath taken me. Forther, it is a great comfort to the godly, that the wycked (whom god dothe vſe as a rodde, to ſcourge the godlye people) go not clere awaye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out puniſhement, whome he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth other ſhamefullye aſhamed, or throughe theyr owne councell, he dothe take them, and bryngeth theym into the ſame dyſtruction, whiche they theyr ſelfes haue ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed
<pb facs="tcp:10370:48"/> &amp; founde out for other. As it is right before god, that he ſhulde rewarde euery man accordyng to his workes. What is ſoo iuſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god? as that they whiche doo oppreſſe the godly in this worlde, and throughe perſecution make them exiles, in the worlde to come ſhall ſuffer the ſame perſecution, whiche they haue doone to other: The godly, that they maye be in reſte with other ſaynctes, whiche commynge from greatte trouble, ſhall nowe receyue the kyngdome eternal. For when we be gon here hence, all labour and ſorowe ſhall ceaſſe, and reſte and ioye ſhall fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe: and to the wycked ſhall fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe cleane contrary, lyke as (we rede in the goſpell) dyd folowe to the ryche glotten. Sonne remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre.<note place="margin">Eſai. 10.</note> &amp;c. Wo be to the Aſſure, the rod
<pb facs="tcp:10370:48"/> of my angre &amp; fury, I wyl teare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, &amp; breke the, as the bough of a tree. Alſo Paule, It is ryght (ſayth he) before god, to gyue afflyction to them, which do punyſhe you, and to you whiche be puniſhed, releaſe and delyueraunce therof.<note place="margin">Rom. 9. Exod. 9. Daniel. 5. Eſai. 10. Micha. 5.</note> Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hereof be Pharao, Baltha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, Daniel, Sennacherib, Saul, Abſalom, the Phariſeis, Caiphas and Pilate. The cauſe is, for he that hurteth one faythefull, hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not onely hym but god: the whiche dothe reuenge the iniurye and wronge done to the faythful, as iniurie done to hym ſelf. as the lorde ſayde to Samuell:<note place="margin">1. Re. 8.</note> They haue not caſt the away but me. He forbiddeth to touche his faythful, ſayinge,<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.</note> Do not touche myne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted, and ſay not yl of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes.<note place="margin">Hiere. 2.</note> They whiche deuour Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:49"/> do ſynne, and yll ſhall come vpon them.<note place="margin">Zacha. 2.</note> He that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of myne eye. They that ſpoyle the,<note place="margin">Hiere. 10.</note> ſhalbe ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Alſo Chriſte, He that hereth you, hereth me: and he that deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſeth you, deſpiſeth me. And ſoo god dydde ſpeake from heauen to Paule,<note place="margin">Acto. 9.</note> ſaying, Saul Saul, why doſte thou perſecute me?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>¶The goodneſſe of god is not to be deſpiſed, or lyghtly regarded before afflyctions. whirby god wyl puniſhe and gyue warnynge. Capi. xiiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GOD THERFORE</hi> giueth warnynge and monition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that men ſhulde repente, and ſo repentynge, ſhulde beleue and receyue grace: and they whiche wyll not beleue, ſhuld be without excuſe, and ſuffer puniſſhemente iuſtely.<note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> So Noe in his tyme dyd
<pb facs="tcp:10370:49"/> admoniſhe men an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth yeres. And Lothe dyd warne the Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. Gen. 19.</note> Alſo Egypte was in peryll to peryſhe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moyſes was ſent. It was ſhewed before by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, that the .x. trybes ſhulde be caryed to Babylon, Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ſhulde be ouerthrowen by the Chaldees, and the peple broughte to captiuitie. Hieremie was ſente, whiche preached forty yeres.<note place="margin">Daniel. 3.</note> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bugodonoſor was made a frayde in his dreame. Soo Chryſte dyd bewayle and ſhewe before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The place of repentaunce with god is before the ſentence gyuen: but not ſo, if it be wrytten: the folyſhe virgins dyd aſke oyle in vayne, when the yates were ſhutte vp. Eſau mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to late, when Iacob had go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the bleſſynge. So the pſalm,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:50"/> Seke the lorde whyle he maye be founde. Kyng Balthaſar dyd not ſeke the lorde, nor dyd not fynde hym: but Nabugodonoſor dyd ſeke hym, and dyd fynd hym. Alſo the vnfaithful miniſters bounden both hand and fote, were caſt out into outwarde darkeneſſe. When the wrothe of the lorde is conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate or at the full, the godlye be punyſſhed with the wycked. The iugement of god, when he is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, is gyuen vppon all, as well good as yll,<note place="margin">Eſai 64. Pſal. 43.</note> as Eſai teacheth. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the pſalm, The godly conceyue a hope of felycitie and grace, as they do confeſſe: We haue not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the.<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.</note> The lorde ſhal not cut awaye his mercye for euer. And they whiche be chaſtened do ſuffer iudgement, and at length do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne mercy. He wyl not be angry
<pb facs="tcp:10370:50"/> for euer.<note place="margin">Pſal. 67.</note> Therfore the lorde dothe punyſhe all the godly, whiche do repent, with peynes in this world, as he punyſſhed Dauid, that he myght make them more lowlyer: he dothe inſtructe them with ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, and maketh them more cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumſpecte and ware. God doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſend before bothe meſſengers and tokens, that men myghte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente: and to theym, whiche wyll not repent, no excuſe ſhall be left: as the prophetes, Chryſt, and his apoſtelles did warne men in theyr tyme, as it is written:<note place="margin">Prouer. 1.</note> Wyſedome ſitteth without the dores, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acheth in the ſtretes, and cryeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loude. &amp;c. He councelleth and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his to repentaunce, that they maye feare, ne leſte he caſte them amonges the blaſphemers. But they be not caſt away, the whiche
<pb facs="tcp:10370:51"/> made aferde by goddes worde, do beleue Chryſt: but rather Chriſte draweth them to hym ſelf, ſaieng, Come to me all you which labour and be burdened and lade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and I wyll refreſhe you. But thou wylt ſaye: The proper worke of god is to fauour and to haue mercy, and therfore he wyll reuoke his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. It is trewe. for it is a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge worke to hym to be angry: for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely, he wolde not the deathe of a ſynner, but rather that he ſhulde be conuerted and liue. But vnder this condition, he wyl reuoke his ſentence, if we knowlege our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:<note place="margin">Ezech. 18.</note> wherby we haue prouoked god to wrothe, and do repent. If the wycked do repent. &amp;c. But Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce is conuertion and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the wycked man, whoſe two partes be contricion &amp; faith.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:51"/> Contrition, is to knowledge the ſynne, and by the iudgement and ſentence of god, truely to be made afrayde, ſayinge, We haue ſinned onely to the: beholde,<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> thou art an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grye. Alſo, I am he whiche haue ſynned. But Fayth is a conſtante truſte of mercy, by the whiche we decree and recken ſurely, that our ſynnes be forgyuen vs for Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake: Then ſhall god reuoke his ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, when there is yet time to pacyfie god. as we rede in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas of the drownynge of the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuites. And the word of god was ſpoken to Eſai: Go and ſay to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechias, This ſayth the lorde god of Dauid thy father, I haue hard thy prayer, and ſeene thy teares &amp; wepynges, beholde, I wyll adde and put to thy days fyftene yeres &amp;c. So Chryſte dyd ſet forthe the
<pb facs="tcp:10370:52"/> fayth of the woman of Chananie, whiche before he ſemed to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye. Is god therfore to be eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med mutable? no: for althoughe he reuoketh the ſentence, whiche he wylleth to be ſecrete and hydde from vs, yet he doth not chaunge his eternall councell: but for this cauſe thoſe thynges be doone by the godly prouydence of god, that the feyth of the ryghtuouſe might be proued. Therfore the decreed purpoſes of god be irreuocable, and can not be called ageyne. nor any man lyuynge canne breake or diſapointe the decree and purpoſe of god, as Eſai witneſſeth, ſaying. The lorde of hoſtes hath decreed it,<note place="margin">Eſai. 14.</note> who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breke or make it voide? he hath put forthe his hande, who can turne hym ageyne? So Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.<note place="margin">Naum. 1.</note> Who canne ſtande before the
<pb facs="tcp:10370:52"/> face of his wrothe and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? And, who is able to reſyſte in the wroth of his fury? Surely, no man nor creature can breake the decreed appoyntement of god, or reſiſte his wrothe. The decree of god may be broken by repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: that is, by ſorowe, that the ſynne is done: and by fayth, which doth certaynely beleue and fele, that al our ſinnes be forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake. This faythe doth ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the iudgement of the lawe. (whiche is the decree of god) whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is his wroth.<note place="margin">Ezec. 22.</note> Wherof Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el ſpeaketh: The lorde ſaythe, I haue ſerched for a man, the which wolde make vp the hedge, and ſet vp hym ſelfe in the gap before me in the londes behalfe. It is ſaid to Moyſes, Let me deſtroy this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. He whiche ſayth, let me, doth
<pb facs="tcp:10370:53"/> ſygnifie and declare, that he maye be letted, whiche by no carnal ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, no walles of defence, nor by no mannes wiſedome, is or can be brought to paſſe, but by the onely faythe in the worde of god, which is Ieſus Chryſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>¶There be dyuerſe craftes of the dyuell, wherby he tempteth, and where one crafte profyteth nothynge, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth many other. Ca. xv.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE</hi> diuel hath not one grin, ſnare, or deceyte, but diuerſe. For he gothe about to deceyue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and ſolitarie people or cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterers, by one polycie, and other which be conuerſante in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and common people, by an other crafte: but agaynſte all the aſſautes of the diuel, there is none ſo ſure and redy a remedy at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as the continuall medytation of
<pb facs="tcp:10370:53"/> ſcripture:<note place="margin">Matth. 4.</note> as Chriſte dydde ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all the aſſautes of the dyuell by the onely meditation and reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of the ſcriptures. For that is the only commoditie and profyte, the continual meditation of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture both by daye and nyght. and ſo Paule ſaith,<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.</note> Take you the hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of helth, the ſworde of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, whiche is the worde of god, wherby we defende all his fyrye dartes and weapons, and vtterly extinguyſhe them. Wherfore it is beſte remedy in the begynnyng of all temptation, to checke the diuel in the mouthe, that it becommeth not vs to do that, whiche he ſtyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and ſuggeſteth vs to do, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallye, bycauſe god prohybiteth and forbyddeth it to be done. that, he can not by any meanes ſuffer: nor he wyll not be ſmytten downe
<pb facs="tcp:10370:54"/> nor dryuen away with one ſtroke or twayne, but he wyl come again as often.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note> For he walketh aboute as a rorynge lyon, ſekynge whom he may deuour. Whom you muſt reſyſt with ſtedfaſt faythe, ſaythe Peter. For the dyuell knoweth howe to bryng forthe the wytneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſcriptures, but falſely of his ſpirite of errour.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>1 If thou be tempted in pryde or vayne glory, anſwere hym agayne.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note>
                     <hi>IT IS</hi> wrytten, God reſyſteth the proude, but to the lowely he gyueth grace.<note place="margin">Eccle. 11. Matth. 16.</note> Aſhes and yerthe, why arte thou proude? He whiche exalteth hym ſelfe, ſhall be made lowe. and he that lowely meketh and ſubmytteth hym ſelfe, ſhall be exalted. So Moyſes and Aaron in the begynnynge were lowelye,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:54"/> but at the laſte they were greate. So Ioſeph was lowely in Egipt, Daniel in Babylon was lowely, the apoſtelles were fyſhers. Pride dydde ouerthrowe Lucifer out of heauen. So Pharao, Nabugod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onoſor, Balthaſar, Holofernes, and other proude kynges: pryde hath caſt them down into extreme myſery.<note place="margin">Luc. 2.</note> The lord hath put downe the myghty from theyr ſeate, and hath exalted the lowely.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>2 If thou be tempted in wrothe or anger.</head>
                  <p>SAy, It is written,<note place="margin">Ia. 1.</note> The wrothe of a man dothe not worke the iuſtice of god.<note place="margin">Ephe. 4. Pſal. 9. Leuiti. 19.</note> Lette not the ſonne go downe vpon your wrothe. Be ye angry, and do not ſynne. Thou ſhalte not hate thy brother in thy harte, but ſhalte tell thy neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour his faute, that thou beare
<pb facs="tcp:10370:55"/> not ſynne for his ſake: nor thou ſhalte not haue in remembraunce the wronge of thy citizens. For wroth ingendreth hatred, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred manſlaughter: and Cayn by hatred killed his brother.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.</note> And eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry one, which hateth his brother, is a mankyller. To hate a man is not only to be of a ſtrange mynde towarde hym, but to denye your neyghbour ſuche workes, as bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue doth require.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>3 If thou be tempted in feaſtynge, or glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony and drounkenneſſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 21.</note>SAy, It is wrytten, Take hede to your ſelues, ne leſt your har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes be ouercome with feaſtynge and dronkennes.<note place="margin">Proue. 23.</note> Whoo is accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? be not they whiche delyte in moche drynking of wyne, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye howe to drynke of cupfulles?
<pb facs="tcp:10370:55"/> Wo be to you,<note place="margin">Eſai. 5.</note> whiche be ſtronge to drynke wyne, and expert to ſet vp drounkennes. Alſo, Wo be to you, that ryſe vp earelye, to vſe your ſelues in drounkennes, and yet at night are more ſuperfluous with wyne.<note place="margin">Prouer. 2.</note> Wyne maketh ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and drounkennes prepareth brawlynge or chydynge.<note place="margin">Oſe. 4.</note> Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wyne, and dronkennes take away the harte. Alſo dronkardes ſhall not poſſede the kyngdome of god. Be you not drounken with wyne, in the whiche is lechery. It is not vnlaufull to drynke wyne, the ſcripture wolde that the body ſhulde be chaſtiſed, that he be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and ſubmyt hym ſelfe to the ſpirite, as Paule ſaythe. Be you fulfylled with the holye goſte, as he wolde ſaye: Be you ſober: for ſo you ſhall be apt to the mocions
<pb facs="tcp:10370:56"/> of the holy goſt. Empty faſters al ſo waxe mad, nor be not mete nor apte for godly thynges.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>4 If thou be tempted in auaryce or couetouſenes,</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Matt. 10.</note>SAy, It is wrytten. What pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleth it to a man, if he wyn all the worlde, and yet leſe his ſoule? Take hede &amp; beware of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſenes.<note place="margin">Luc. 12. Hebr. 13.</note> Let your maners be far from couetouſenes, &amp; be ye con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tented with the thinges whiche ye haue. Who y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſyreth to be made riche,<note place="margin">Eccle. 11.</note> ſhall not be without ſynne. Of this thyng are examples. Gie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi Helizeus ſeruante,<note place="margin">2. Re. 5.</note> was ſtryken with the leproſy. Agayne, Acham was ſtoned.<note place="margin">Iudic. 7.</note> The ende or intent of couetouſenes, is to lyue longe, to lacke nothynge, that he be not in danger or loſſe of any thing. It is the fountayne &amp; roote of vnbelefe.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:56"/> The lord therfore wil, that we put our confidence in him, that we caſt al our carefulnes &amp; hope in hym: and then ſhal it come to paſſe, that he ſhall prouide al thynges mete and neceſſary for vs. Infidelytie then alonely in all matters ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs ſo carefull and penſyfe, for bycauſe we truſt not God, nor beleue ſtedfaſtly in hym.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>5 If thou be tempted with hungre, pouertie, or carefulnes of lyuynge,</head>
                  <p>SAy, It is wrytten: Man ſhall not lyue in bread onely, but in euery worde that procedeth frome the mouthe of god.<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> They whiche ſeke the lorde, ſhal want no good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. I haue bene yonge,<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.</note> and am waxen olde, and I haue not ſeene the ryghtuouſe forſaken.<note place="margin">Pſal. 54.</note> Lay thy care on the lorde, and he ſhall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe
<pb facs="tcp:10370:57"/> the.<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.</note> Thou openeſt thy hand, and filleſt euery creature with thy bleſſynge.<note place="margin">Pſal. 146.</note> Whiche gyueth meate to the hungry. Be ye not careful. Chryſte fed with fyue barly loues and two fyſſhes,<note place="margin">Matt. 6.</note> fyue thouſande men.<note place="margin">Marc. 6. 3. Re. 17.</note> The rauens brought meate to Helias. Alſo, the angel brought meate frome heauen to Helias. Therfore the care of temporalle thynges muſte be left to god: For fode is gyuen, and is not gotten with labour, yet god wylleth vs to labour.<note place="margin">Gen. 3. Pſal. 127.</note> In the ſweat of thy face. &amp;c. For thou ſhalte eate the labours of thy handes. We muſte therfore labour, for bycauſe we ar made for that purpoſe: and for-bycauſe ſoo is the wyll of god, to whoſe deuyne wyll we muſt obey. Alſo he hath inioyned vs to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, to macerate and mortifie the
<pb facs="tcp:10370:57"/> fleſhe, to profyte our neyghbour, and to prouide for our neceſſitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>6 If thou be tempted of ydelnes,</head>
                  <p>SAy thou:<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> In the ſweate of thy face, ſhalt thou eate thy bread. For the lorde hath appoynted the chyldren of Adam to labour,<note place="margin">Prouer. 6.</note> At the example of the Piſmyre. And Chryſte was a carpentar,<note place="margin">Matth. 13.</note> and wrought with his handes tyll the tyme of his preachynge. Agayne, Noe planted a vineyard.<note place="margin">Gen. 9.</note> He whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che tylleth the londe, ſhalbe ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.<note place="margin">Proue. 12.</note> Conſider thou godly chryſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, how god curſeth ydelnes, and howe moche he abhorreth it. For experience teacheth, that frome thens ſpryngethe forthe all kynde of vice. Ezechiell ſayth, The ſinne of Sodom was pryde, plenty of breade, habundance, and ydelnes.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:58"/> Wherfore god hath commaunded vs to labour, and hath bleſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that labour. for without the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge of god all labour is in vain.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>7 If thou be tempted of ſecurytie to be without feare.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Matt. 25.</note>SAy thou, Watche ye, for ye knowe not the houre. He that ſtudyeth, let hym take hede he fall not. Adam ſtode not in paradiſe. The people of Iſraell, as often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes as they were made fat, and increaſed to a multitude, ſo often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes fell they backewarde, and forgatte theyr lorde god. Dauid, when he was at reſte, and ſittyng at home without reſiſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, he was made an adulterer and a murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and nombred the peple in his great fury.<note place="margin">Daniel. 4.</note> So Nabugodonoſor counteth hym ſelfe happye. The
<pb facs="tcp:10370:58"/> ryche man in the goſpell promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge hym ſelfe eaſe and reſt, dyd here. O fole. &amp;c.<note place="margin">Luc. 12.</note> Ezechias in try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation continued ryghtuouſe. in proſperitie he was ouercome of vayne glory. For the lord forſoke hym, and his harte was auanced. and therfore is ſecuritie reproued. for throughe it, is neglected the commaundement of god. Chriſte ſayde before, that the houſholder being abſent, and al were aſlepe, came the ennemie &amp; ſowed cokell.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>8 If thou be tempted of fornication and adultery,</head>
                  <p>SAye thou, It is wrytten:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> He which cleaueth to an harlot, is made one body with her.<note place="margin">1. Teſ. 9.</note> This is the wyll of god, your ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ye abſteyne from fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Nother horemayſters,<note place="margin">1. Co. 6.</note> nor
<pb facs="tcp:10370:59"/> adulterers ſhal inherite the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of god. Sodom and Gomer ſhewe manyfeſtly, how moch god puniſheth that ſynne. Alſo of the ſame ſynne, there are other pey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, execution, induration, and the contempte of god. Alſo Dina the doughter of Lya, for whoſe whoredome were the Sichimites kylled. Agayne, the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, thou ſhalt not commytte adultery. Let there be no harlotte of the doughters of Iſraell: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther horemaiſters of the ſonnes of Iſraell. but thou wylt ſay, Howe can I auoyde this yll? with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to god, to gyue the continencie. Alſo by the word of god and auoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng it, as ſayth Paule. Flee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. Ioſeph is an example, whiche fled bycauſe he wolde not be kendelyd with the fylthye loue
<pb facs="tcp:10370:59"/> of the wyfe of a nother.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>9 If thou be tempted with lyinge or lyghte wordes,</head>
                  <p>SAy thou: That lyenge is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beden in the law: that we ſhuld not ſpeake falſe thynges. Thou ſhalte fle lyenge. Ye ſhall not lye.<note place="margin">Exod. 23. Leuiti. 19. Pſal. 5. Ephe. 4.</note> Thou ſhalt dyſtroy all them that ſpeake lyes. but lyenge ſet aſyde, let euery man ſpeake the truthe to his neyghbour, for as moche as we be members to gether. Peter kylled Ananias and Saphira, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they lyed. I ſaye vnto you,<note place="margin">Matt. 10.</note> that of euery ydel worde that man ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall gyue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compte in the daye of iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. Agayne, Let no fylthy communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion go forth of your mouthe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10370:60"/>
                  <head>10 If thou be tempted of confeſſynge the goſpell, or ſufferynge perſecution for the goſpell,</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Matt. 10.</note>
                     <hi>HE THAT</hi> receyueth not my croſſe, and foloweth not me, is not worthy of me.<note place="margin">Matt. 16.</note> If any wyll come after me, let him forſake him ſelfe, and take his croſſe, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe me. For he that wyl ſaue his ſoule, ſhall leſe it. Contrarywyſe, he that leſeth his ſoule for my ſake ſhall fynde it. He that wyl confeſſe me before men, I wyl confeſſe him before my father.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> I am afflycted and perſecuted for the goſpell, as a wycked dooer. Iohn bare the croſſe for the truthe ſake. So the Apoſtelles reioyſed, bycauſe they were cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted worthy. So Daniel. For chryſtian men are hated of the world, and deſpiſed in this world. Therfore this world knoweth not<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10370:60"/> you, for bicauſe it knewe not him: whiche ſpeake yll of you.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. Io. 15.16. 1. Tim. 3.</note> The ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt is not aboue his lorde: All they whiche wyll lyue godly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>11 If thou be tempted of the faythe of thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes: as wherfore beleueſt thou not that, whiche thy forefathers haue beleued,</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BE YE</hi> not made lyke to your fathers. and I haue ſayde,<note place="margin">2. Para. 3.</note> Theſe euer erre in hart.<note place="margin">Pſal. 94. Zacha. 2.</note> Be ye not as your fathers were. We muſte not conſider our parentes, nor kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, nor longe cuſtome, but onely the wyll of god: the wyl of god is to beleue. This is the wyl of god,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note> that ye beleue in hym, whome he hath ſente.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>12 If thou be tempted of ſtraunge relygion or of worſhyppynge of ſaynctes, pyctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, ymages, or men,</head>
                  <p>SAy thou, It is wrytten,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.</note> Thou ſhalte worſhyp thy lorde god,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:61"/> and hym onely ſhalte thou ſerue. Wherfore I wyll gyue godly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to no creature vnder heuen, but to the lyuynge god onely.<note place="margin">Philipp. 2.</note> For to me (ſayth he) ſhall euerye knee bowe, of all in heuen, in erthe, and in hel.<note place="margin">Exod. 41.</note> Agayne, I wil not giue my glory to any other. Here if thou be tempted of blaſphemie, thou maiſt ſuffer it in noo caſe. and when the name of god is blaſphemed, we muſt crye, and alſo ſet our lyfe in ieoperdy, if nede ſo be. For no tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation dothe ſo ſeperate vs frome god, as dothe blaſphemye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>13 If thou muſte dye, and leane wyfe, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and thy dere frendes,</head>
                  <p>SAy, The lorde ſhal be theyr de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender. for god bothe wyll and is able to cheryſſhe myne, to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe and defende them.<note place="margin">Exod. 22. Pſal. 36.</note> For he is the father of the fatherles and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:61"/> I forget thynges behynde my backe,<note place="margin">Philipp. 3.</note> and indeuour my ſelfe to thoſe thynges, that are before my face. Agayne,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note> They whiche haue wiues, let them be as though they had none. and they that wepe as thoughe they wepte not. We muſte be dylygente, that we leaue our wife and children wel inſtruct and taughte in the feare of god. For the feare of god is better and more preciouſe, then a cheſt full of golde and ſyluer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>14 If thou be tempted of condemnation, that thou arte condemned of god.</head>
                  <p>SAy thou,<note place="margin">Roma. 3.</note> That is no condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them which are graf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fed in Chriſte. that is, ſynne canne not dampne them, be it neuer ſoo moche in them: for they are made one body throughe fayth. For the ſynne, whiche they haue, is forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:10370:62"/> them, and is not imputed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them for Chryſtes ſake, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are graffed, whiche is the hed, and we the membres.<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.</note> He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth in the ſonne, hath euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng lyfe.<note place="margin">Rom. 10. Pſal. 36.</note> Al they which beleue in hym, ſhal not be confounded. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rightuouſe falleth, he ſhal not be broyſed, for the lorde ſetteth his hande vnderneth hym.<note place="margin">Prou. 24.</note> The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſe falleth ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes in a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>15 If the dyuell ſaye, thou arte a ſynner, and arte not graffed in Chriſte.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CHRISTE CAME</hi> into the worlde to make ſafe ſynners. For the deathe of Chryſte hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied for all ſynnes,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.</note> through his ſtrokes,<note place="margin">Eſai. 53.</note> are we all made ſafe. For he hath borne our ſynnes in his body.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. Ephe. 1.</note> by whom we haue redempti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on throughe his bloude. I came not to calle the ryghtuouſe, but
<pb facs="tcp:10370:62"/> ſynners. They whiche are hole,<note place="margin">1. Ioan. 2.</note> nede not the phiſition. And if any doo ſynne, we haue an aduocate and ſpokeſman to the father, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. The godly haue ſynne alſo, but god imputeth it not.<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note> The ſayntes do euer pray, Forgyue vs our treſpaces. If we confeſſe,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.</note> that we haue ſynnes, he is faithful and ryghtuouſe to forgyue vs our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to clenſe vs from all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quytie. We haue many exaum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Marye Magdalyn, alſo Paule was a blaſphemor, of the thiefe whiche went from extreame puniſhement to ioye, of zacharie. Matth. and Peter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>16 If he continue and ſaye, but thy ſynnes paſſe the ſonde of the ſee.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AS FAR</hi> as the eaſt differeth from the weſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.</note> ſo far of hath he made, that our ſynnes are from
<pb facs="tcp:10370:63"/> vs.<note place="margin">Eſai. 1.</note> If thy ſynnes be as redde as ſcarlet, yet ſhall they be as whyte as ſnowe: and if they be as red as purple, yet ſhall they be as whyte as woll.<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note> I haue ſayde, I wyl con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my vnryghtuouſnes agaynſt me, and thou haſte forgyuen the wyckedneſſe of my ſynne.<note place="margin">2. Re. 12.</note> I haue ſynned lorde.<note place="margin">Eſai. 38.</note> &amp;c. And the lord hath taken thy ſynne frome the. Thou haſte caſte all my ſynnes behynde thy backe.<note place="margin">Miche. 7.</note> And he hath throwen al our ſynnes in the bottome of the ſees,<note place="margin">Ezech. 18.</note> If the wycked ſhall repente. &amp;c. For god hath promyſed remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes to them that repent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>17 If he ſaye, ſuche promyſes are made to the godly, thou arte an apoſtata and a loſte man.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 15.</note>
                     <hi>AND</hi> the prodigall ſonne was loſte, and an apoſtata, yet he founde grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo great is the loue
<pb facs="tcp:10370:63"/> of god towarde vs, he wyl ſaue al them that wyll knowlege theym ſelues. He hath ſo great care euen for the leaſte, that are loſte, in the ſyght of the worlde. Examples ar Dauid, Peter, and the thefe, and alſo Paule: God ſometyme ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his ſayntes to erre for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but he calleth again at length He bryngeth theym in to dyuerſe troubles, that they maye knowe hym. He yeldeth theym vp ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes into the handes of Satan, and his membres, that they maye knowe howe moche eaſyer it is to ſerue hym, then the prynce of this worlde. The confeſſion of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall chylde is greate:<note place="margin">Luc. 15.</note> Father I haue ſynned agaynſte heauen and agaynſte the. So Dauid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50. Eſai. 64.</note> I haue done yll agaynſte the. Lo all oure rightuouſnes are as a blody cloth
<pb facs="tcp:10370:64"/> of a woman.<note place="margin">Luc. 1.</note> This mekeneſſe god beholdeth, he is moued with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, as the father of the prodygall chylde.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> We are therfore receyued without all our meryte or deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, for we are yet ennemies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>18 But god hereth no ſynners nor ſtrayers awaye,</head>
                  <p>SAy thou, It is truthe, god he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not ſynners, which repent not, whiche ſorowe not, nor are borne agayne by faythe: thoſe are the vngodly and hypocrites, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che praye not to god: and if they praye, yet praye they not in fayth. Then ſhall they call on me,<note place="margin">Prouer. 1.</note> and I wyll not here theym. Soo in the pſalm,<note place="margin">Zacha. 7.</note> They ſhall crye, and I wil not here them. But he graciouſly hereth the contrite, and them that repente, and are borne agayne by faythe in Chriſte.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> A contryte and
<pb facs="tcp:10370:64"/> humble harte o god, thou wylt not deſpiſe.<note place="margin">Iaco. 5.</note> The buſye prayer of the ryghtuous is moche worthe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>19 But thou commeſt very late with thy contricion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CONTRARY</hi> wyſe anſwere thou,<note place="margin">Luce. 23.</note> None commeth to late into the vyneyarde of the lorde, as witneſſeth the hyſtory of the thefe, whiche was full of wycked dedes, and yet ſayde to Ieſus, Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre me lord, when thou ſhalt come into thy kyngedome. And Ieſus ſayde vnto hym, Trewelye I ſay vnto the, this daye. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>20 But he hadde a ſtronge faythe in god, whiche thou lackeſt,</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ANSVVERE,</hi> Therefore pray I with the apoſtels,<note place="margin">Luc. 17.</note> O lorde increaſe faythe within vs, helpe our vnbelefe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10370:65"/>
                  <head>21 What if all holy ſcripture be falſe, for they were men, which ſpake it and wrote it?</head>
                  <p>SAy thou contrary, Moyſes, the prophetes, and apoſtelles were truely men, but yet they neyther ſpake nor wrote with the ſpirite of man, but with the ſpyrite of god, they ſet not forthe theyr owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, but thoſe thynges whiche eyther they ſawe with theyr eyes, or receyued of the lorde. So ſayde the lorde to Moyſes:<note place="margin">Exod. 4.</note> Who hath made the mouthe of man? Or who hath made the dome and the deffe? the ſeinge and the blynde? not I? Goo forthe then, and I wyll be in thy mouthe, and wyll teache the what thou ſhalt ſpeake. Say not, I am a chylde,<note place="margin">Hiere. 1.</note> for thou ſhalte go to all thoſe, to wome I wyll ſende the to, &amp; thou ſhalt ſpeake al that, that I ſhall commaundethe.<note place="margin">Luce. 21.</note> He
<pb facs="tcp:10370:65"/> gyueth the apoſtelles both mouth and wyſedome. Agayne, Ye are not whiche ſpeake, but the ſpirite of your father. So Paule:<note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> I dare not ſpeke any thyng, which Chriſt hath not wroughte by me.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 1. Ioh. 1.</note> If any man ſpeake, let hym ſpeke as the wordes of god. that we haue hard, that we haue ſeene with our eyes.<note place="margin">Luc. 1.</note> as they haue delyuered vs, whiche from the begynnyng haue ſeene it with theyr eies.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note> But thoſe thinges which we haue ſene with our eies. Al ſcripture heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly inſpired.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 2. Pet. 1.</note> The prophecie in old tyme, was not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by the wyl of man, but the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men of god ſpake, dryuen with the holy goſt.<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note> As it is nowe reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to his holy apoſtelles and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes by ſpirite:<note place="margin">Matt. 22.</note> So Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth Dauides wrytynges. Howe doth Dauid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſpirite call him
<pb facs="tcp:10370:66"/> lorde? Certaynely I am fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, and doute nothinge at al, that the holy ſcriptures are inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from heauen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>22 If the temptator ſaye, thou haſte not kepte the lawe of god, wherfore thou arte accurſed.</head>
                  <p>SAy thou: Chriſt, whiche was made a curſe for vs,<note place="margin">Galath. 3.</note> hath rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs from the curſe of the lawe. Agayn,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> Euacuatyng, and taking awey the lawe of commaundmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſet in decrees.<note place="margin">Colo. 2.</note> Takynge away the handewrytynge agaynſte vs, which is in decrees, and is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to vs.<note place="margin">Roma. 6.</note> For ye are not vnder the lawe, but vnder fauour, delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from ſynne. For the deathe of Chriſt hath delyuered vs from the lawe. For truely by Chriſtes deth, we are now in conſcience fre from the lawe, that is, from the wrothe
<pb facs="tcp:10370:66"/> of god, and euerlaſtynge deathe. For the lawe can not be fulfylled of nature, for it is ſpirytuall, as vndoubtedly the apoſtels decreed. The yocke that neither. &amp;c. Again,<note place="margin">Acto. 15. Deuter. 5. Luc. 18.</note> who can gyue them ſuch a minde? Whiche is impoſſible to men.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>23 If he ſay, thou muſt forſake the worlde.</head>
                  <p>VVhat then? Anſwere thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary wiſe. I ſhal obteine he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. For bleſſed ar the dead,<note place="margin">Apoc. 14. 1. Ioh. 5. Ibidem.</note> which dye in the lorde. Agayne: All the world lieth in wickednes. Agayn, All thyng whiche is borne of god, ouercometh the world: and this is the victory, which ouercometh the world, our fayth. Who is he, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ouercometh the worlde, but he that beleueth, that Ieſus is the ſonne of god? I am ſure therfore in Chriſte. All the worlde ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe with his luſtes and deſyres.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:67"/> Agayne.<note place="margin">1. Ioan. 3.</note> Loue not the worlde, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe thynges whiche are in the world. We ar ſtrangers in this worlde, and citizens of heauen. Ye ſonnes of men, howe longe are ye harde harted?<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> Why loue ye vany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ſeke lyes? Agayne: Howe lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g loue you infancy or childhode, and foles deſire thoſe thinges, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che are hurtfull? Agayne: Vanitie of all vanities,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.</note> and all thynges ar vanitie.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.</note> The cauſe is this: for all thynges whiche are in the worlde, as luſte of the fleſhe, concupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the eyes, and pryde of lyfe, are not of the father, but of the world, and the world paſſeth, and his luſt alſo, but he that dothe the wyll of god, taryeth for euer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>The ende.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:10370:67"/>
            <head>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>THE PREPARA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION TO DEATHE, AND</hi> howe they which be in point of deathe, ſhulde be comforted, the .ii. boke.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶What is deathe. Cap. i.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>EATHE IS</hi> NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge els but a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration or diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bodye. It is a quiet reſt from the afflyctions and troubles of this worlde, in the whiche they that be deade, be ſo refreſhed and newely made, that from thenſe they ſhall ryſe far aboue all other moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye, not into a lyfe which ſhall dye ageyne, as it is in a ſlepe, but into an euerlaſtynge life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶What is the cauſe of deathe. Cap. ii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE CAVSE</hi> of deathe is ſynne: For out of ſynne deth
<pb facs="tcp:10370:68"/> flowed, and is the puniſhement, or peyne, or rewarde of ſynne, or the reuengeaunce of yll thynges, as the holy ſcripture beareth witnes, Fyre,<note place="margin">Eccle. 39.</note> hayle, hunger, and deathe, be created for puniſhement, as wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſeth the pſalme. For anger and dethe be in his indignation,<note place="margin">Pſal. 29.</note> and lyfe in his wyl:<note place="margin">Roma. 6. Hiere. 3.</note> The wages or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of ſynne is death. In what daye ſo euer thou ſhalte eate of it (that is, thou ſhalte ſynne) therof thou ſhalt dye. God dyd not make deathe,<note place="margin">Sap. 1.</note> nor doth not reioyce in the deſtruction of the lyuynge. Alſo, Throughe the malyce and enuy of the dyuell,<note place="margin">Sap. 2.</note> death hath entred. And Paule ſaythe.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> By one man ſynne entred into the world, and through ſynne deathe.<note place="margin">Ezech. 33</note> And in Ezech. I wil not the deathe of a ſynner, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he conuerte and tourne
<pb facs="tcp:10370:68"/> from his ſynne and liue: Alſo, The ſoule whiche ſhall ſynne, ſhal dye. Therfore where deathe is, there neceſſaryly ſynne dydde go before, whiche dwelleth in vs, whiche we haue by inheritaunce, whiche is ſpronge forthe into vs all: of the whiche ſynne the fyrſt father to vs was Adam, from whom we haue by inherytaunce origynall ſynne, whiche is a naturall dyſpoſytion and inclination, to ſynne, whiche hath with hym in felowſhip blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of harte, dulneſſe towardes vertue, the loue of hym ſelfe, the hatred of god, fleynge frome the croſſe, hatred of the lawe, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daynynge of his neyghbour. For by Adams diſobedience our fleſhe is become diſobediente to god, ſoo long as it is not enſpyred with the holy goſt: and for the ſayde ſynne
<pb facs="tcp:10370:69"/> of Adam, al we be called ſynners: And ſo in hym we be all deade: for we be his fleſſhe and his chyldren of his owne ſubſtaunce: He is the grayne and ſede, of whom all we be ſpronge out. As he is deade, ſo ſhall we dye: and frome Adam is ſpronge into vs, bothe orygynall ſynne, and deathe, the peyne of ſynne, is come forthe: And the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the dyuell, to whom our nature is ſubiecte, and in whome the dyuell vſeth crueltie, and doth exerciſe it with feare and all kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of myſerye, and alſo doth kyl: And moreouer enforceth to al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vnhappines, to blaſphemy, murther, and hatred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Two maner of deathes. Cap. ii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE ONE</hi> is of the body or of nature, to whome all men
<pb facs="tcp:10370:69"/> be ſubiecte: for al haue ſinned, and haue broken the lawe of god: that is, when this bodyely lyfe is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken aweye, when we gyue vp the gooſt, and do not occupie this mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall lyfe: As it is wrytten to the Hebrewes:<note place="margin">Hebre. 9.</note> It is ordeyned and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, that all men ſhall dye ones: and after that iudgement. By A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams ſynne nature is ſubiecte of neceſſitie to dye, as Ieſus Sirach wryteth.<note place="margin">Eccle. 40.</note> There is a heuy yocke vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon the chyldren of Adam, frome the daye of the commynge oute of theyr mothers wombe, vntyll the daye of theyr burial, into the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all. The other deathe is of the ſoule, or of fayth, or of helth. When the vnbeleuers, drowned in theyr wyckednes, not carynge for god, nor deſyrynge god, nor aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng forgyuenes of god, be made
<pb facs="tcp:10370:70"/> bondemen to eternall darkeneſſe, which is called euerlaſtyng death: Whiche is a perpetuall feare of conſcience throughe the wrothe of god,<note place="margin">Sap. 5.</note> whiche Satan doth encrece. Exaumple of theſe two maner of deathes is the riche gloton,<note place="margin">Luc. 16.</note> which beinge deade, was buried in hell, and Lazarus the begger beinge deade, and caryed of angelles into the boſome of Habram. This man hath comforte: and contrary wiſe, the ryche man was punyſhed and buried in hel: that is, he died with an yll conſcience: he ſawe in his deathe his owne wyckedneſſe and damnation, as al wicked men do. This is the worme,<note place="margin">Eſai. 66.</note> whiche dothe not dye. Euen then the foliſhe vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins do firſt ſee,<note place="margin">Matt. 25.</note> that the wiſe haue oyle. Then it commeth to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, to whom they haue doone
<pb facs="tcp:10370:70"/> bothe good and euyll: There the lawe dothe fyrſte ſhewe hym ſelfe (the goſpell beinge taken awaye) thenne they ſeke for grace, but all to late and in vayne.<note place="margin">Prouer. 1</note> There god dothe cut of all hope of recouerye of helthe or fauoure: the ſentence of the cruell iudgement of god is then, as ſayth ſaynt Iames:<note place="margin">Iaco. 2.</note> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement without mercy ſhall be to them, whiche haue not done mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. I haue hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gered,<note place="margin">Matt. 25.</note> and you haue not gyuen me. &amp;c. Therfore the worde of god doth teache vs, how we ſhulde avoyde eternal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and howe we ſhal be ſaued: whiche if we neglect, &amp; ſet nought by, there is no cauſe why we ſhuld haue any further hope. Of theſe two kyndes of dethes the pſalmes make mention:<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> The deathe of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners is yl. And contrarywyſe, The
<pb facs="tcp:10370:71"/> deathe of ſaynctes is preciouſe in the ſyght of god.<note place="margin">Pſal. 113. Pſal. 6. Matt. 7. Matt. 11.</note> Alſo, Go frome me all you workers of iniquitie: I knowe you not: Come to me all you that do labour and be burde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and I wyll refreſhe you: Alſo In theyr ſynne they ſhall dye. And Paule ſayth:<note place="margin">Philipp. 3.</note> Whoſe ende is death Alſo of the feythefull is wrytten: They ſhall not faute, al they whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che truſte in hym,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> The Lord doth kepe theyr bones, and one of them ſhall not peryſſhe, or be broken.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> There is no damnation to theym whiche be in Chriſte Ieſus.<note place="margin">Apoc. 14.</note> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the deade, whiche die in the lorde. As there is two lyues, a yerthely and an eternall lyfe: ſoo there is two deathes, the one a tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porall, the other an euerlaſtynge deathe. The erthly lyfe hath a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge and a endynge, and is
<pb facs="tcp:10370:71"/> ſubiect to many miſeries: and this lyfe no chriſten man dothe greatly eſteme, but ſaith daily with Paule Chriſt is my lyfe,<note place="margin">Philipp. 1.</note> and death is lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre. And if it fortune me to lyue in the fleſhe, then it is profytable to me to worke: and what I ſhall choſe, I know not, I am conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of theſe twayne, deſyrynge to be diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt: whiche thynge is moche better for me, but to lyue in the fleſſhe, is more nedefull for you.<note place="margin">Galath. 6.</note> Soo in an other place, God forbeade, that I ſhulde reioyce in any thynge, but in the croſſe of our lorde Ieſus Chriſt, by whom the world is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfyed vnto me, and I vnto the worlde. I lyue, but not I onely:<note place="margin">Gala. 2.</note> but Chriſt liueth in me. for in that that I lyue in the fleſhe, I lyue in the faithe of the ſonne of god, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:10370:72"/> loued me, and gaue hym ſelfe for me. Therfore he that knoweth not Chriſte, nor doth not truſte in hym, feareth death, as that which threteneth and bryngeth eternall ruine and deſtruction: but he whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che knoweth Chriſt, and hath him doth not feare death: whom Chriſt beinge victor, hath ouercome and ouerthrowen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶To the efecte and faythfull, eternall deathe by Chriſte is ouercome. Cap. iii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THIS</hi> is the great comfort of them, that be in the painges of deathe; whiche comforteth and lyfteth vp the fearefull myndes: that is, that Chriſte hath vtterlye abolyſſhed deathe, takyn awaye ſynne, and that ſurelye throughe Chriſte, they ſhall obteyne remyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſynne, be reputed ryghtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:72"/> and haue euerlaſtynge lyfe. Therfore Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſed ſede, the ſonne of god, came downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heuen, and became manne: by his croſſe, deathe, and reſorrection, hath ſaued vs, and delyuered vs from eternall deathe: and he pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for vs all our dette, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in the epiſtle to the Hebrewes: Ones he is offered,<note place="margin">Hebre. 9.</note> that he ſhulde take awaye the ſynnes of manye. Alſo,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.</note> He hath ones ſuffered for our ſynnes. And,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.</note> The bloude of Ieſu Chryſt hath made vs cleane from all our ſynne. And,<note place="margin">Matth. 1.</note> Thou ſhalte call his name Ieſus. for he ſhall ſaue his people frome theyr ſynnes. Alſo,<note place="margin">Hebr. 2.</note> That through death he ſhulde put awaye hym, whiche had rule ouer death, that is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, that he myght delyuer them, whiche all theyr lyfe were brougte
<pb facs="tcp:10370:73"/> in bondage, through feare of deth. For verylye he hath delyuered vs from the power of Synne, that it ſhulde not kyll vs: frome the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of deathe, that it ſhoulde not condemne vs: from the power of affliction, that it ſhulde not greue vs: from the power of the dyuell, that he ſhoulde not deſtroye vs: &amp; hath reſtored vs to iuſtice, ioy, lyfe, and to the beſte and mooſte myghty god, that is, he hath made vs fre men and partakers of god, whiche before were captyues and bondmen to the deuyl. So our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities dyd caſt vs hedlynge into the depeneſſe of hell, and there did drowne and bury vs: but god mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with mercy, hath caſte all our iniquities vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſhulders of his ſonne, delyuerynge vs all frome ſynne deathe and hell, hath ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed
<pb facs="tcp:10370:73"/> for vs, whiche of god is made to vs wyſedome, iuſtice, holynes,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> and redemption. Whiche hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hym ſelfe for our ſynnes, that he myghte delyuer vs frome this preſent yll world: And vnder ſuch forme by Chriſte we be delyuered frome deathe ſynne and hell, that they vtterlye haue noo maner of ryght in vs, nor can not deſtroye and damne vs, As Oſee ſayth:<note place="margin">Oſee. 13.</note> I wyll delyuer them from the hand, that is, from the power of hel, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deathe I wyll redeme them: O deathe, I wyll be thy deathe. O hell, I wyll be thy bytte. Deathe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> where is thy ſtynge? Hell, where is thy victory? Thankes be to god whiche hath gyuen vs vyctorye throughe our lorde Ieſus Chriſte. So great is the power of faythe, and we be broughte into ſo greate
<pb facs="tcp:10370:74"/> lybertie: throughe fayth. We fele puniſhemente in this worlde, but through fayth we peryſhe not. We be kylled, but we ſhal not dye: We bren in hel fyer, but we be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in dede: and ſoo of all the reſte, whiche be not taken awaye frome the beleuer.<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> In the worlde ſaith he, ye ſhal haue affliction. &amp;c. Nor the beleuers be not delyuered from the felynge of theym in this world, but they be delyuered from the power and rule of them, and the ſtynge is taken from theym, wherby all men dyd peryſhe. The chriſten man is therfore ſure, that as deathe eternall coulde not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle agaynſte Chriſt, ſo lykewiſe ageynſt him it hath no power. For Chriſt hath taken away ſinne, brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynge in iuſtice: he hath ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led deathe, gyuynge lyfe: He hath
<pb facs="tcp:10370:74"/> obteyned victorye ouer hel, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtringe eternal glory. For as in Adam all dyed: ſoo in Chriſte all ſhall be reuyued. For by Adams diſobedience ſynne death punyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that moſte cruell tirant Satan dyd chalenge bothe ryght and rule ouer all, howe many ſoo euer were borne of hym. The lawe of ſynne is to kyll: the wages of ſynne is death: the ryght of death is to damne, the ryght of afflycti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is to greue &amp; make heuye: the ryght of the dyuell is to deſtroye: Into al theſe rightes and powers Adam by his diſobedyence, hath caſte vs. And Adam then had ben vtterly extinct and vndone, if that he hadde not be comforted ageyne &amp; reuyued with the word of grace. But he was receyued vnto grace, and the father dyd take from hym
<pb facs="tcp:10370:75"/> feare of deathe and anguyſhe: for he did fele and perceyue the wroth of god, and god to be his ennemy, and alſo all creatures, ſoo that he could not tel, which wey to tourne him: This feare I ſay, the father hath taken away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him through the moſt ſwete abſolution and pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe of grace, when he ſayde vnto the ſerpent:<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> I wyl put enmite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twyxte the and the womanne, and that ſede ſhal al to breake thy hed. This worde when Adam dyd here and beleue, he was holpen and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered, and came from hell, and nowe beleued the worde of god: thinkyng vnder this forme: This god hath ſpoken, whiche can not lye or deceyue. In this faythe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam dyed, and after Adam all the faythfull vnto Aabraham, whiche dyd alſo cleaue faſte to this word,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:75"/> thynkynge thus: he wyl come, yea ſuerly at the laſte he wyl come: by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the lorde hath ſo promyſed, whiche canne not lye: and in this faythe they were ſaued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Althoughe the godly dye, yet they ſhall lyue. Cap. iiii,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE</hi> godlye and iuſte people haue moſt comfort, although in this lyfe they be put to deathe, and ſeme to be forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, caſt into hell, and as ſhepe ordeyned to be ſlayne:<note place="margin">Roma. 8.</note> As ſcripture wytneſſeth of them. For thy ſake we be iuged as ſhepe ordeined to be ſlayne. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, I thynke veryly,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> that god hath ſhewed, that we whiche be the laſt apoſtelles, are as it were apointed to ſuffer deathe: For we,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> whiche lyue, be alway delyuered to death for Ieſus ſake: yet they do not diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peyre,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:76"/> no not in death, but as they which be ſure, that they ſhall paſſe through deathe to life eternal, and crye to god, and ſuffer the hand of the lorde, and be pacient, and put theyr hope in god. Alſo they haue this comforte, that their deathe is good and precyouſe. They alſo knowe, that throughe Chryſtes deathe, deathe is ouercome and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolyſhed.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. Oſee. 3. Gen. 3.</note> Deathe is ſupped of in victory. O Deathe, I wyll be thy deathe: The ſede hath broken the heade of the ſerpente. Therfore if any man taken in the panges of deathe, do holde faſte and beleue this worde: in the myddel of death he ſhall haue lyfe. for verylye the chriſtyans doo lyue, when they be eſtemed and thought to dye.<note place="margin">Sap. 5. 2. Cor. 6. Ioh. 16.</note> The rightuouſe ſhal lyue for euer. And ſoo Paule ſaythe: Beholde we be
<pb facs="tcp:10370:76"/> euer as dyenge, and yet we lyue: Alſo Chriſt ſayth.<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> In me you ſhal haue peace, but in the worlde, you ſhall ſuffer oppreſſion. And,<note place="margin">Sap. 3.</note> The tourment of death ſhal not touche them. Alſo,<note place="margin">Eſai. 26.</note> Thy deade perſonnes ſhal lyue, they ſhal ryſe with theyr bodyes. He ſhall not taſte deathe.<note place="margin">Io. 5. et. 11</note> And he whiche beleueth in me, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe he were deade, yet he ſhal lyue. They ſhall not taſte deathe.<note place="margin">Marc. 9. Sap. 2.</note> The iuſte man, althoughe he be preuented with deathe, yet he ſhal be refreſhed. Alſo,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.</note> Thou ſhalt not ſuffer thy holyon to ſe corruption. Alſo,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32. Ioh. 5. et. 11. et. 3.</note> That he may pulle out from deathe the ſoules of them. He ſhal paſſe ouer from deathe to lyfe. He ſhall not ſee eternall deathe. He ſhall not dye for euer: He dothe not peryſhe, but hath eternall lyfe: Seke god,<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.</note> and your ſoule ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:10370:77"/> lyue:<note place="margin">Eſai. 55.</note> Bowe your eares, and come to me: here you, and your ſowle ſhall lyue.</p>
               <p>¶Theſe places ought to be well noted, for the comforte of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſe eies deathe is preſente: whiche if they beleue in Chriſte, they be not loſte, but haue eternall lyfe. Therfore they be not called onely deade, but the deade of god, as ſuche as dye in the lorde: for ſuche do ryſe ageyne in glory, and none other,<note place="margin">Danie. 12.</note> as it apereth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Daniel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶The deathe of the godly, is a ſlepe. Ca. v.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHRISTE</hi> calleth the death of the godly, a ſlepe. Lazarus our frende ſlepeth.<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.</note> For by the bene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyte and goodnes of Chriſt, death is made a ſlepe, which by his deth, hath changed deathe into a ſlepe. So Paule dothe call the feythful,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10370:77"/> whiche be deade, ſlepers, ſayinge. I wyll not you to be ignorante of them, that ſlepe. So Steue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlept.<note place="margin">Acto. 7.</note> And ſo the godly to the outwarde ſyght, and perceuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, dieth. But withoute doubte that death is but a ſlepe. For how many ſo euer dye in Chriſte, all ſlepe in hym, and he ſhall reyſe them in the laſte daye. I haue ſlept, and do ſlumber,<note place="margin">Pſal. 3.</note> and I haue ryſen. Here ſlepe betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth deathe of the body, as in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis, Abram ſlepte with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note place="margin">Pſal. 4. Pſal. 15.</note> I wyll ſlepe and reſt in peace to god with other. Alſo, My fleſhe ſhal reſt in hope. Therfore in deth not ſo moche the deathe it ſelfe, as ſuer lyfe and reſurrection, is to be conſidered to theym, whiche be in Chriſt, accordynge to Chriſtis ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge. He that ſhall kepe my word,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> ſhall not ſee deathe euerlaſtynge.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:78"/> Howe ſhall he not ſee deathe? ſhal he not fele it? Shal he not dye? no veryly, but he ſhal ſe onely a ſlepe, and beholdyng ſtedfaſtly with the eies of faythe in the reſurrection, by deathe he ſhall ſo paſſe awaye, that ſurely he ſhall not ſee deathe? And death veryly to hym ſhal not be deathe.</p>
               <p>¶All theſe thynges be begonne in baptiſme, and be fynyſſhed in the ende of lyfe.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> For we be buryed with him throughe baptiſme in to deathe. Therfore faythe exerciſed with diuers paſſions, cauſeth, that naturall deathe to the faythefull, is but a ſlepe. For the faythful die ſuerly in hope, and loke after the laſte daye and the commynge of Chriſte: This ſecuritie they gette in this lyfe by the ſpirite of fayth, that they maye ſaye with Paule:
<pb facs="tcp:10370:78"/> By hope we be made ſafe?<note place="margin">Roma. 8. Rom. 5.</note> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. Hope dothe not confound. That is to dwell in the Paradyſe of god, the kyngedome of heauen in the churche of the lyuinge god: And the lord ſayth,<note place="margin">Leuit. 26. Eſai. 31.</note> To ſlepe with out feare. To ſyt in the beautie of peace, in the tabernacles of fayth, and truſte, and in a ryche reſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Baptiſme is a comforte in the poynte of deathe. Cap. vi.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SVCHE</hi> as be at the poynte of deathe, ought to take comforte and be ſtronge, in that they know, they carye with them bothe letter and token, which is baptime: wher by theyr death is incorporate with the deathe of Chriſt, and that it is not theyr deathe, but the deathe of Chriſte. Wherfore let them ſuerly truſte, that they ſhall ouercome,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:79"/> as the deathe of Chriſt hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. For baptime is a ſure token of the paſſynge ouer from deathe to lyfe. And as we knowe ſuerlie, that Chriſte paſſed through death to lyfe: So let vs not doubte, but that we ſhal ſuerly paſſe throughe deathe to lyfe. Chriſte hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſynne and death: Let vs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge doubte, but that we ſhall ouercome ſynne &amp; deathe. Synne ſhal not beare rule ouer you.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of this thynge was the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge ouer the ſee, whiche was the paſſynge ouer from deathe to lyfe. So in baptime we receiue a token of deathe: that by death of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, we myght truſt ſuerly to come to the trewe lyfe. In baptime Pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rao, with all his hoſte, dyd lye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foote to vs, that is, throughe fayth in the worde of promyſe: we
<pb facs="tcp:10370:79"/> haue eſcaped the tyrannye of the prynce of darkeneſſe, with all vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: ſo that the lorde wyll not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute them to vs, nor they can not take awaye from vs the entree or goinge in to the kyngdome of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. But yet not withſtandynge, ſynne dwellyng in our fleſhe, doth not reſte in the meane tyme, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulte vs, that is, vncleane affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whiche muſte be put awaye with dayly mortifieng of the fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſyres, vntyll our baptime be fully co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plete and finiſhed in deth. So greately the hope of all chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten men dothe ſtande in baptime, and ſo beginneth from death: that deathe to vs is wynnyng, that is, an entraunce to lyfe.<note place="margin">Roma. 6.</note> Be you igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that all we, whiche be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into Chriſte Ieſu, are baptiſed into his deathe? For we be buried
<pb facs="tcp:10370:80"/> together with hym by baptime in to deathe, that as Chriſte was rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp from the deade, by the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his father: euen ſoo we alſo ſhuld walke in a newe lyfe.<note place="margin">Colo. 2.</note> You be buried to geder with him through baptime, in whom you are alſo ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen agayne with him.<note place="margin">Gala. 3.</note> Who ſo euer of you be baptiſed in Chriſte, haue put vpon you Chriſte.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.</note> Baptime is the promyſe of a good conſcience towardes god, wherby we be ſure, that god is pleaſed with vs. It is therfore a token, that we be dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from the dyuel, and a ſygne of our tranſlation from the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Satan, in to the kynge- of Chriſte, that we be reconſyled vnto god, it is a token whiche bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth wytneſſe of the good wyll of god towardes vs. Therfore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that thou arte baptyſed,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:80"/> that is, that thou haſt receyued re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynnes: that thou haſte made a couenaunt with god, that thou arte delyuered frome the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, deathe, and ſynne, reconſiled to god. This is a great comforte agaynſte deathe, the dyuell, and ſynne. So the promyſe made to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of the ſede to come, had ben ſufficiente: yet god dyd put therto circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that Abraham might haue a ſure token of goddes good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes towardes him, that he was ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepted of god. So baptime is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of goddes fauour and good wyll towardes vs, throughe the worde of promyſe, wherevnto is knyt an erneſt bargaine of a good conſcience with god. For fyrſt god maketh promyſe with vs, that he wyl forgyue vs that faute and ble<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſhe, whiche we haue drawen by
<pb facs="tcp:10370:81"/> originall ſynne, from our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that he wyl receyue vs into his fauour, and that he wyll not onely forgyue vs our ſynnes, but alſo not ley or inpute them to our charge. We agayne do bynde our ſelues to god by lyke reaſon, that we ſhall mortifie our fleſhe all our lyfe tyme, and purge out our olde leuen, our concupiſcence, deſyres, and diſpoſitions to do ſynne, and vtterly to caſt out all the dregges: and to wreſtel agaynſte and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye forſake the worlde, the dyuell, and al theyr pompes: Therfore if thy conſcience be troubled and vex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed with the borden of ſynne, thou mayſt pray on this maner. O lord god, remembre thy promyſe, that thou haſte made to vs: thou haſte promyſed to vs in baptime, remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of ſynnes and eternall lyfe,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:81"/> when thou dyddeſte ſaye:<note place="margin">Marc. 16.</note> He that beleueth and is baptyſed, ſhall be ſaued: nor do not make voyde thy couenaunt, nor let not thy wordes be in vayne, whiche haue paſſed thy mouthe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.</note> Thou ſhalt performe that thou haſt promyſed, thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not deny thy ſelfe, neyther our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, or infidelitfe, or any other thynge can make voyde thy feyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promyſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶The godlye knowe the tyme of dyinge to be determyned of god. Cap. vii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VNTO</hi> the godlye this is a gret comfort, that they know that deathe is not in the power of tyrantes, nor put in the hande of any creature, leſte they ſhoulde be troubled, ouer moche carefull for deathe: but that they maye dye as chyldren, when pleaſeth the lorde.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:82"/> For ſoo wryteth Eccleſiaſtes:<note place="margin">Eccle. 3.</note> All thynge hath tyme: and al thynges vnder heauen, haue theyr conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient ſeaſon: A tyme is of byrthe, and a tyme of deathe.<note place="margin">Iob. 14.</note> and ſo Iob. Thou haſte appoynted to hym a a tyme, whiche he ſhall not paſſe. Alſo the pſalme:<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note> Thou haſt lymit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted a tyme, whiche they ſhall not ouer paſſe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.</note> Beholde, thou haſt put my dayes to a certayne nombre. And ſo Chriſte doth comforte his. One heare ſhal not fall from your heade without the wyll of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note place="margin">Matt. 10.</note> Alſo, My houre is not yet come.<note place="margin">Ioh. 2. 1. Reg. 2. Eſai. 38.</note> So the mother of Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, God dothe kyll and reuiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. And, The yeres of lyfe, be of the lorde. As he promyſed to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechias:<note place="margin">4. Re. 20. 2. Re. 7.</note> Beholde, I wyl adde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy days .xv. yeres. So. When thy dayes ſhall be ended. For the
<pb facs="tcp:10370:82"/> corporal lyfe is determined of god with certayne lymyttes: and with god is a certayne pointe and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſet to euery mannes lyfe: and alſo to the ſame, the yeres, mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, oures, and alſo the mynutes of houres: And alſo the heares of your hedde be nombred. Therfore if our heares be noumbred in the ſyght of god, howe moche more ar the mynutes and artycles of our lyfe nombred before hym? We can not therfore lyue any longer then the lorde hath appoynted: We ſhal not dye, althoughe we be in the greatteſt peryl and extreme ieoper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye, before our houre. Therfore it ſkylleth not what maner of death, or with what inſtrument, ſwerde, fyer, water, ſodeyne death, or that thou be taken awaye by chaunce, before the courſe of nature requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:10370:83"/> it. For god hath gyuen the houre, the meane, and that kynde of deathe: Whiche doth not force, whether thou dye of this death or that deathe, of a lyttell wounde or a great: of whom the tyme, bothe of our lyfe and deathe is determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſette. Alſo many dye by tempeſtes or hayle. And yet do not thou condemne, as wycked, ſuche as be ſmytten with lightning. For the iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of god be rare and vnknowen in priuate perſonnes: whiche for as moche as perteineth to hym, careth not, whether oone dye of this deathe or that. Many tymes innocentes and baabis do dye. But thou wylt ſaye, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dye wylfullye, throughe theyr own raſhenes, the whiche myght haue lyued lenger. Somme haue caſt away them ſelfes hedlong. &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:83"/> Coulde they not haue preſerued theyr lyfe? I aunſwere noo. God gaue that houre, that meane, and that kynde of deathe. which thing experyence dothe teache. Some deadely wounded, are lyghtly hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, and do lyue: Some other are ſcarſelye hurte, and yet they die. Some Aſtronomers aſcrybe this to the ſterres, and ſome to fortune: but holy ſcripture attributeth it to god, with whom the tyme both of our lyfe and deathe is lymytted, who alſo careth not, whether thou dye of a great or ſmal wound: that he maye confounde all wyſedome and mannes imagination. Soo that it is a thynge moſt like mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vayne, and fruſtrate, to be afrayde or curiouſe of any maner of deathe. For there is noo cauſe why it ſhuld make any man aferd.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:84"/> For other the appoynted tyme of deathe is not yet come, or elles if it be come, he, ouer whom it ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth, wolde nat prefer any pleaſure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deathe. For death (as I haue ſayde) hathe his apoynted tyme, lyke as Chriſt ſayth:<note place="margin">Luce. 21.</note> The heares of your heade doo not fall. If che heares of your heade doo not fall without the apointed wyl of god, by what meane maye the hole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy dye without the fire wyl of god? So great is the care of god ouer the godly, whoſe lyfe, death, yeres, dayes, houres, and mynutes of houres, he hath in his hand, which can not die but at the houre apoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted of god.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Notwithſtandyng the vngodly ſhall not liue out halfe theyr dayes. Cap. viii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AS</hi> holy ſcripture witneſſeth in all places. In the pſalm.
<pb facs="tcp:10370:84"/> The deceytefull ſhall not liue out halfe theyr days. Alſo Iob,<note place="margin">Pſal. 54. Iob. 16.</note> In the tyme whiche is not his, he ſhall make an ende. And, The feare of the lorde, prolongeth the lyfe. the yeres of the wycked be ſhort. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly be euer redy, watchyng whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lorde ſhall come, whether it be in the firſt watche, or in the fourth, they in the meane tyme, folowe theyr callynge, as long as the lord wyll, nothynge determyninge for them ſelfe, nothynge carynge for theyr lyfe, whether it ſhall ende on the morowe, or .x. yeres after: for they haue lyued all theyr tyme, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe they dye yonge:<note place="margin">Sap. 4.</note> As the wyſe manne ſaythe, Thoughe the rightuouſe be ouertake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with deth, yet ſhall he be in reſt. The vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do appoynte vnto them ſelues longe tyme, as he whiche ſayde in
<pb facs="tcp:10370:85"/> Luke:<note place="margin">Luce. 12.</note> My ſoule, thou haſt moch goodes layde vp in ſtore for many yeres. They do ſo, and lyue ſo, as they ſhuld liue a long ſeaſon: but in the myddel of theyr lyfe, beyng voyde of faythe, they be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, in the daye whiche they dyd not loke for, and the houre whiche they dyd not knowe.<note place="margin">Matt. 25.</note> So the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe virgins, beinge vnredye, in the myddell of theyr dayes, were called away. So for the moſt part alwayes, the iudgemente of god dothe catche the vngodly, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, negligent, and not watching. So in Daniel,<note place="margin">Daniel. 5.</note> Balthaſar the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g was ſlayne in the nyght of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. Alſo in the goſpell, The tumultuous ſeruauntes, the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domytes, and they whiche were in the tyme of the flodde. the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deathe dothe alwaye fynde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redy:
<pb facs="tcp:10370:85"/> but all the godly tary vntyll theyr full tyme, that is, they be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer redy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>¶The godly alſo in the tyme of hunger, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, and warre, be punyſhed, and dye with the wycked. Cap. ix.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT IS</hi> trewe, that the godly be punyſſhed with the vngodlye, where the wrothe of god is conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate. For the iudgemente of god, when he is angrye, is gyuen vpon all, bothe good and bad: but the godly conceyue a hope of felycitie and fauor.<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.</note> He ſhall not withdraw his mercye for euer. And ſoo they, that be puniſhed, ſuffer iugement, and at the laſte ſhall opteyne mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. For the godly do knowe, that god dothe puniſhe ſinners, which doo repente in this lyfe, as he pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed Dauid, that he myght hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble them, enſtructe theym in ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:86"/> and make them more ware and circumſpecte. And althoughe they dye in the tyme of hunger, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, or warre with the wicked, yet they knowe it to be done by the good wyll of god. And bycauſe they know that they ones ſhal die: Therfore they offer them ſelues to the good wyll of god, which dothe al thinges after the councel of his wyll.<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> And they knowe, that they haue a tyme apoynted to dye, and they deſyre to be dyſſoluyd in the tyme of dienge appoynted by god, and to be with Chriſt. Otherwiſe, Nother peſtylence, hunger, nor warre can hurte the godly, except the appoynted tyme of deathe, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned of god, be preſent. For god can well delyuer his, as he dyd in tymes paſte delyuer Lothe, Noe, Daniel, Ieremy, and other: as
<pb facs="tcp:10370:86"/> Iacob being caryed with his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in to Egipte: And lyke wyſe the Iſraelytes in Egipt.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.</note> For theſe coulde not dye, but in theyr houre: So al the feythful can not dye, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be in the greatteſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll, and in extreme deſperation, but in theyr houre. Then wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall they feare deathe? They can not lyue lenger then the lorde hath appoynted, nor die any ſoner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶To whom they that dye oughte to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte theyr ſpirite. Cap. x.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>STEVEN</hi> dydde yelde vp his ſpirite into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of Chriſt For it is he that hath ouercome deathe,<note place="margin">Acto. 7.</note> &amp; in death he doth quicken vs. This is he, which ſayd:<note place="margin">Matt. 12.</note> Come vnto me al you that labour and be burdened, and I wyl refreſhe you. And farther, this is he, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:10370:87"/> oughte to be called vpon, that he delyuer vs in afflyction, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue our ſpiryte in the houre of deathe.<note place="margin">Luc. 23.</note> So dyd Chryſte, Father I commende my ſpiryte in to thy handes.<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.</note> So Dauid: Lord, I com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mende my ſpirite into thy handes. There it ſhall be ſuer, vnder the ſhadowe of thy winges, thou ſhalt kepe it vnhurte: and that whiche is taken away, thou ſhalte reſtore. Let the ſpirite retourne to the lord whiche dyd gyue it.<note place="margin">Eccle. 12.</note> Alſo Chriſt to the thefe.<note place="margin">Luc. 23.</note> This daye thou ſhalte be with me in Paradiſe. This Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radiſe is a true and perfyte quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in Chriſt, amiable, ioyful, and moſte ſwete: And ſo Lazarus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the boſome of Abraham, to whom Lazarus ſoule was caryed by angelles, that is, he is contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the handes of our god and
<pb facs="tcp:10370:87"/> of the lorde Ieſu Chriſte, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the moſte pleaſante lyfe. For the boſome of Abraham, is the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe made to Abraham of the ſede whiche is Chriſte, in whom all the godly from Abraham vnto Chriſt, were kepte: and as many as dyd beleue, were preſerued.<note place="margin">Philipp. 1.</note> So Paule deſyreth to be louſed, and to be with Chriſt. And in an other place Whether we lyue or dye, we be the lordes. Therfore the hande of the lorde receyueth the ſoules of ſuche as be faythfull, and they reſt qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly in the hande and word of god, vntyl the day of iudgement come. For they be in peace, and entred in to reſt. Tourne my ſoule in to thy reſt. For they be in pleaſure, in ioy,<note place="margin">Sap. 3. Hebre. 4. Pſal. 114.</note> in bleſſednes, in ſuertie, in Chriſt, and with Chriſt in comforte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10370:88"/>
               <head>¶The body is buried, but it ſhall ryſe agayne in the laſte daye. Cap. xi.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT IS</hi> the onely comfort of the godly, to holde ſuerly in all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie this article of our faythe, that is to ſaye, the reſurrection of the fleſſhe, the whiche oughte to comforte the ryghtuouſe: bycauſe through the grace of god they ſhal be reuiued, and reyſed vp, as well the body as the ſoule, the ſoules to iuſtice, the bodyes to glorye. This hope the wycked haue not. For theyr bodyes ſhall be the more pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and ouerthrowen downe to the grounde, althoughe they haue ſemed here to be mighty: but their bodyes ſhal be reyſed vp and quic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kened by the worde of god, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thynges obeye. Of whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe the very emptye and dry bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhall be partakers.<note place="margin">Ezec. 37.</note> This ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:10370:88"/> the ruler, the lorde of theſe bones: Beholde, I doo brynge into you a ſpirite, and you ſhal be quickned, and I wil put vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſinnowes, and I wyll reyſe vp fleſhe vppon you, and I wyll couer you with a ſkynne, and I wyll put in you a ſpirite, and you ſhal lyue, and you ſhall well knowe, that I am the lorde.<note place="margin">Iob. 19.</note> Thou ſhalte reyſe vp my ſkynne, which this fleſſhe beareth. And I do knowe, that my redemer dothe lyue, and at the laſt he ſhall reyſe me vp of duſt, and ſhal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe my body about with ſkynne, and in my fleſhe I ſhall ſe god.</p>
               <p>¶Veryly the holye ſcripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, that the reſurrection of the deade ſhall be, for that the bodye, for his nature and power, ſhall be made perfyte in the knowledge of the lorde. The glorye of the ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:10370:89"/> redoundeth into the reformed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. In the meane tyme, the ſowle lacketh not the knowlege of god and of his Chriſte. For he is with Chriſte, and hath in hym eternall lyfe, and moſte lyuely and bleſſed knowlege,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.</note> But the perfyt bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is not, vntyll the bodyes be borne agayne.<note place="margin">Danie. 12.</note> Many, which ſlepe in the duſte of the erthe, ſhall ryſe agayne, ſome into eternall lyfe, &amp; ſome into ſhame. The deade ſhall ryſe agayne, and they ſhall be rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp,<note place="margin">Eſai. 26.</note> that be in graues. Thy deade ſhall lyue lorde, and they whiche dye in me, ſhal ryſe again. Your bones ſhall bloſſome as the graſſe.<note place="margin">Eſai. 66.</note> Therfore we beleue, that there ſhall be a reſurrection of this fleſhe by goddes power, and that the deade ſhalbe quickened ageyn by the ſpirite of Chryſte. Whiche
<pb facs="tcp:10370:89"/> ſhall quicken your mortall bodies throughe his ſpirite,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> dwellynge in you. The fyrſte ground of this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle is, that Chriſte is ryſen. If Chriſte be preached,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> that he hath ryſen from deathe, howe can ſome of you ſaye, that there ſhall be no reſurrection? If Chriſte hath ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, we ſhall alſo ryſe. Chriſte, the fyrſte begotten of the deade, hath ſufficiently declared his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. What ſo euer was in Chriſte the heade, the ſame ſhall be in his membres: and we ought to beleue, that we ſhall ſuerly atteyne that, whiche our heade nowe dothe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne, accordynge to the meaſure of our fayth. The fruites of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes reſurrection, is our reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and wakynge. for if god hath reyſed vp our lorde Ieſu, he ſhall alſo reyſe vp vs through him. So
<pb facs="tcp:10370:90"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10370:90"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10370:91"/> Paule. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. through the hole chapter. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. And the deade in Chriſte ſhall ryſe.<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> Do not meruel, for bycauſe the houre ſhall come, that all ſuch as be in theyr graues ſhal here his voyce, and ſhal come forthe. &amp;c. Alſo thy brother ſhall ryſe.<note place="margin">Cap. 11.</note> Martha anſwered: I knowe that he ſhall ryſe in the laſte day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>¶In the panges of deathe, and in all temta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the remedies be to be lerned of the ſufferaunce of Chriſt. Ca. xii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE</hi> example of lyuynge and dienge is ſet forth before our eies in Chriſtes lyfe and paſſyon: for ſo ſayth Peter.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> Chriſte is affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for vs, leauynge vs an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that we ſhuld folowe his ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. But howe can we folowe his ſteppes? Here thou: If thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue thy croſſe on the, as Chryſte
<pb facs="tcp:10370:91"/> techeth the. How can that be,<note place="margin">Matt. 10.</note> ſaieſt thou: Beholde, take an example. If thou be puniſhed with ſickenes reken with thy ſelfe, howe it is not to be compared with Chryſtes crowne of thorne and his nayles. If thou be reſtrayned of thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyres and luſtes, remembre Chriſt led hyther and thyther. If pryde ſtyrre thy mynde, remembre Chriſt nayled on the croſſe betwene two theues. Wherof Eſai ſaythe.<note place="margin">Eſai. 53.</note> And we haue ſene hym, and there was no fayerneſſe in hym, and we haue deſyred the deſpyſynge of all men. If thou brenne in lechery, or any other yll deſyre, remembre howe Chriſtes tender fleſſhe was all to torne with ſtrypes, thriſt through, and al to broken. Wherof the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture ſayth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.</note> They haue nombered all my bones. If thou be vexed
<pb facs="tcp:10370:92"/> with enuy or deſyer of reuenging, thinke with thy ſelfe, that Chriſte dyd preye to his father for theym, whiche crucified and ſcorned him. Whiche when he was reuyled, did not reuyle ageyne.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. Eſai. 53.</note> As a ſhepe led to be ſlaine. If ſinne troubleth the, caſte thy ſelfe vpon Chriſte, beleue all his to be thyne, and that by his worke thou arte ſaued. If thou loke ſo onely in Chriſte, thou ſhalt haue peace, and thou ſhalt reioyce that god is thy god. And although thy ſynne be great, yet the grace of god is moche greatter. Therfore ſaye: Althoughe I alone hadde commytted all the ſynnes of the worlde, they were vtterlye none, if I maye obteyne the grace of god throughe Chriſte. God ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his to fall, yea and that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes greuouſely, as Dauid and
<pb facs="tcp:10370:92"/> Peter: that they myghte ryſe and thanke god more feruently. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no ſynner ſhulde deſpeire, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge that ſo great men haue ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo greuouſly, and by the grace of god haue repented and amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded theyr lyuynge. If Sathan do tempte the of predeſtination, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou be amongeſt them, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be ordeyned to the kyngedome of heauen, be deafe, takynge ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſte, whiche hanging on the croſſe ſayde nothynge at all to this, when they ſayde: He hath truſted in god, let him deliuer him if he wyll. So Daniel,<note place="margin">Danie. 3,</note> When the kyng of Babylon ſayd: And what god is he, that maye delyuer you oute of my handes? They aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: we ought not of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to anſwere the. Beholde, our god, whom we worſhyppe, maye
<pb facs="tcp:10370:93"/> delyuer vs frome this fornace of hot burnynge fyer, and out of thy handes O kynge. So thou muſte commytte all the matter to god, whether thou be predeſtinate or no, do not curiouſly ſerche out the maieſte of god,<note place="margin">Prou. 25.</note> leſt thou be oppreſt of his glory. In trouble and deth it ſemeth to manye, that god is a ſlepe, and vtterly forſaketh them, as Chriſte cryeth. God, yea my god, why haſte thou forſaken me. So the goſpel ſetteth forthe to vs an example of them, to whome it ſeemed,<note place="margin">Marc. 5.</note> that Chriſte ſlepte in the ſhyppe. But nowe Chriſte (deathe beinge ouercome) hath promyſed, he wyll be to vs a ſauiour, as it is in Mat. xi. Come to me al you that labour &amp; be bordened,<note place="margin">Matth. 11.</note> and I wyll refreſhe you.<note place="margin">Luce. 12.</note> Agayne, Feare not lyttell flocke, for it hath pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:10370:93"/> your father, to gyue to you a kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome. Therefore by ſuch examples of the goſpell, weake men oughte to be encouraged, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſemeth, that Chriſte is a ſlepe: that be of inconſtante and wauerynge min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, whiche doubte, whether god be mercifull to them, and whether god be in them. They ought to be moniſhed, that they truſt conſtant<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to Chriſte, that although Chriſt ſeme to them to be a ſlepe, yet lette them continewe, and the lorde wil reuenge and delyuer theym out of all theyr euylles, ſoner than it can be ſpoken. Eſai ſayth:<note place="margin">Eſai. 54.</note> for a lyttel ſeaſon at a pynche, I haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the, and in greatte mercies I wyl gather the together.<note place="margin">1. Reg Iob. 13 cap. 5.</note> The lord leadeth downe to hell, and bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth from thenſe ageyne. yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe he kyl, yet I wyll truſte
<pb facs="tcp:10370:94"/> in hym. He dothe wounde, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth remedy: he ſmyteth, and his handes ſhall make hole.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>¶They that be dienge, muſte be exhorted. to forgyue. Cap. xiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note>
                  <hi>BICAVSE</hi> god commandeth, Forgyue, and it ſhal be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you. and putteth thervnto a condition, He that dothe not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue his brother, to hym god doth forgyue nothynge: and if god do not forgyue ſynnes, we can not be ſaued.<note place="margin">Luc. 16. Marc. 11.</note> Forgyue, and it ſhal be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyuen you. And when you ſhall ſtande prayinge, forgyue, if you haue any thynge agenſt any man, that your father alſo may forgiue you.<note place="margin">Matt. 5.</note> When thou offreſt thy gift at the aultare, fyrſt reconſile thy ſelfe to thy brother.<note place="margin">Matt. 18.</note> If you wyl not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue eche of you, your brothers
<pb facs="tcp:10370:94"/> fautes, &amp; that with al your hartes: your father wyll not forgyue you.<note place="margin">Colo. 3.</note> If any man haue a quarel ageinſt his brother, as Chriſt hath forgy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you, ſo do you forgyue. So in the prayer of the lorde, we deſyre forgyueneſſe to be done to vs, as we forgyue them, whiche be our detters: that is, that we forgyue them, of whom in any thinge we haue ben hurte, eyther in dede, to be wrongefully handeled, or elles in worde to be ſhamefully intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And to theym that be at the poynte of deathe, this ſhoulde be mynded, If they at any tyme haue hurte or endamaged theyr neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or taken any thynge frome hym by extortion or robberye, or haue defamed any man. Here alſo they muſte doo as Chriſte dyd on the croſſe, lette them praye for all
<pb facs="tcp:10370:95"/> theyr ennemies, and forgyue them theyr wronges with all theyr har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. And if any thynge of theyrs be taken awaye by thefte, lette them not requier it agayn with viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. If they haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away any thing of a nother mannes, let them yelde it agayne, if they may: or let them labour, that it maye be reſtored: nor let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kepe ſecrete any thyng, but confeſſe theyr faute, be ſorye that they haue offended, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre forgyueneſſe. If for lacke of ryches they be not able to make ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tisfaction: it ſhall be ſuffycyente, that they forgyue other, whiche haue harmed them, other in body or goodes. If they forgyue theym with all theyr harte, god wyll for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them the wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g done to other: As Chriſte teacheth.<note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> If you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue men theyr offences, your he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
<pb facs="tcp:10370:95"/> father ſhall forgyue you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Suche as be diynge ſhulde be admoniſhed, that they receiue the Sacrament of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes body and bloud. Ca. xiiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT IS</hi> a great token of the ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable loue of god and of his abundant mercy towarde vs, that in his ſupper he wolde ſhoulde be wytneſſed, that Chriſte dothe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and gyue hym ſelfe to vs, and dothe ioyne vs to hym as his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres: that we maye knowe, that the lorde loueth vs, hath reſpecte to vs, and ſaueth vs. Forthermore in this ſupper, we here Chriſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge to vs, fedynge vs with his body, proferyng vs, that we ſhuld drynke his bloud for eternall lyfe: where he ſaythe, Take, eate you,<note place="margin">Matt. 26. Marc. 14. Luc. 22. 1. Cor. 11.</note> this is my body, whiche for you is gyuen. Do you this in my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce. Lykewiſe after he hadde
<pb facs="tcp:10370:96"/> ſupped, takyng the cuppe, he ſaid: This cuppe is the newe teſtament in my bloude, whiche is ſhedde for the remiſſion of your ſynnes. Do you this as oft as you ſhal drinke it in the remembrance of me. Good brother, thynke that theſe wordes be ſpoken to the. prynte them moſt depely in thy mynde. for when he ſpeaketh to all, he ſpeaketh alſo to the, to the, to the I ſay, they profit All thynges, whiche Chriſte hath ſuffered, ſhall profite the no leſſe, then they do helpe Peter &amp; Paule. This ſacramente is veryly bothe commanded &amp; inſtituted of Chriſt him ſelfe, for the remyſſion of our ſynnes and eternall lyfe. For the promyſe ſoundeth ſoo, the whiche he that receyueth by fayth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth that whiche he ſaith <hi>(Gyuen for you, and Shed out for you)</hi> hath and
<pb facs="tcp:10370:96"/> obteyneth without doubte remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his ſynnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Diuerſe conſolations, that the life and tyme of affliction is ſhorte. Cap. xv.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT IS</hi> a greate comforte, that affliction ſhall not endure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.<note place="margin">Roma. 8.</note> The afflictions of this tyme, are not worthy of the glory, whiche ſhall be ſhewed vppon vs. The eie hath not ſene,<note place="margin">Eſai. 64.</note> nor the eare hath not harde. &amp;c. the ioyes that god hath prepared for his electe.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> Through many troubles we muſt enter into the kyngedome of god.<note place="margin">Acto. 14.</note> Our trouble, whiche is but tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and lyght, worketh an exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, and an eternall weyght of glory vnto vs whiche loke not on the thynges that are ſene, but on them, whiche are not ſeene. The ſoules of them,<note place="margin">Apoc. 6.</note> whiche were kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb facs="tcp:10370:97"/> cryed out vnder the aulter. to whom it was anſwered, that they ſhulde reſte yet a lyttell tyme. As a lyttell mynute of an houre vntyl the wroth be paſſed by.<note place="margin">Eſai. 26.</note> Alſo Chriſt in the goſpel calleth the time of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flyction,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16. Eſai. 54,</note> A lyttell tyme. A lyttell whyle you ſhall not ſeme. In dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe for a lyttell ſeaſon I haue forſaken the: but in eternall mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies I haue gathered the togeder.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶The comfort of wydowes &amp; Orphans.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THOV</hi> wylte ſaye, I am now a wydowe, and haue no man, which careth for me, here Dauid, whiche ſaythe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.</note> To the fatherleſſe and wydowe thou ſhalte be a hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.</note> Alſo, The poore is left to the, &amp; alſo to the fatherleſſe thou ſhalte be a helper. And Chriſte ſaythe. I wyl not leaue you fatherleſſe:<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> that
<pb facs="tcp:10370:97"/> is, without helpe. So great care hath god ouer the fatherleſſe and wydowes, that he wyll comforte theym in theyr trouble. Hereof we lerne, that we alſo ſhoulde be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with pitie towardes the wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and fatherleſſe, and that we ſhulde aide and ſuccour them: For this is a pure and an vndefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led religion before god the father,<note place="margin">Iaco. 1.</note> to vyſete the fatherleſſe and wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes in theyr trouble. God doth diligently commende to vs this ſorte of men, bothe in the lawe and in all the prophetes, thretenynge greuous punyſhemente to them, whiche eyther do oppreſſe them, or elles doo not ſoccour and delyuer them, when they be oppreſſed. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ody .xxii. Eſai. i. &amp; .x. Iere. v. &amp; .xii. Zacha. vii. So Paule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth Timo. to honour the widowes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10370:98"/>
                  <head>¶The comforte of women trauelynge with chylde.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> chylde is in the hande of god, and is not borne, before the tyme appoynted, whiche is not in our power, but in the wyll of god, at whoſe hande we muſt loke and ſeke for fauor and helpe. And ſuerlye the lorde is nyghe to them, whiche call vpon hym in trouthe. He wyll fulfyll the wyll of theym,<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.</note> whiche feare hym, and wyll here theyr prayer, and ſaue them. But we muſte conſyder, that all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges haue theyr tyme, and that all thynges vnder heauen, paſſe forth by certayne lymyttes and ſpaces. There is a tyme of byrthe,<note place="margin">Eccle. 3.</note> and a time of dyeng. The tyme that god hath ordeyned, muſte be loked for in the faythe of goddes promyſe. The promyſe is this, Thou ſhalt
<pb facs="tcp:10370:98"/> bryng forth thy children, although with peyne, but he promyſeth the delyuerance and byrth. This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe requireth feythe. For he that promyſeth, is able to performe. And more ouer, it requireth obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that the woman be obediente to the wyll of god: vppon whome this croſſe is layd by god the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful father. For it is a great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye of god, that god deliuereth the ſoule from miſery, and vexeth the body with myſery, the ſoule I ſay, is delyuered, and is the doughter of god by faythe: as Paule wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, ſayinge.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> The woman ſhal be ſaued through bearyng of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if ſhe continue in fayth, loue, and ſanctification, with ſobernes. And Chriſte ſaythe: The woman,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> when ſhe trauayleth, is in ſorowe, bycauſe her hour is come: But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10370:99"/> ſhe hath brought forth her chylde, ſhe remembreth not her trybulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for ioye that a man is borne in to the worlde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶A comforte for them that lamente the deade.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>COMEN</hi> honeſtie and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our neyghbour requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that we adorne and worſhip the burialles of our frendes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſlepe in the lorde, with conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient mornynge. But we muſt not lamente and mourne of vngodly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſuperſticion, as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feythefull heathen do, whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue not the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ded, which knowe not, that god liueth, and careth for vs, althoughe our frendes dye. For of theym Paule ſayth:<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.</note> We wyll not bretherne that ye ſhuld be ignorant of them that
<pb facs="tcp:10370:99"/> ſlepe, that ye ſorowe not, as other do, which haue no hope. For if we beleue that Ieſus died, and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne: euen ſo them alſo, whiche ſlepe by Ieſus, ſhall god brynge with hym. Here humanite and the workes of mercy are not condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.<note place="margin">Gen. 23. et 50. 2. Re. 1.</note> For Ioſeph mourned his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Abraham lamented his wyfe Sara: Dauid bewayled Saul. and alſo certayne relygyous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones buryed Steuen,<note place="margin">Acto. 8. Ioh. 19.</note> and made great lamentation vpon hym. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodemus and Ioſephe of Arama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thie, are prayſed, bycauſe they bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Chriſte. Therfore Paule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth not moderate mourning and ſorowe, whiche ſpryngeth of faythefull charitie: but he conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the immoderate heathenyſhe ſorowe and mourning, as vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſuperſtitious. For the hope
<pb facs="tcp:10370:100"/> of Chriſten men is perfytely aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the dead peryſhe not, but ſlepe:<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.</note> as Chriſte ſaythe, Lazarus our frynde ſlepeth. Therfore to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the dead by affection of loue, is the duetie of charytie, but it is hethniſhe and vngodly, to lament the deade of infidelytie. For it is gyuen vs naturally, to bewayle the deathe of them, whiche in their liues were derelye beloued of vs, but we muſt remembre the ſaying of holy Iob, The lorde hath gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> and the lorde hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye. Some tyme our parentes, our dere frendes, our wyfe, and our chyldren be taken away from vs, that we maye lerne the wyll of god, and haue a reſpecte onely to god the gyuer, and not to the gyftes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10370:100"/>
                  <head>¶A conſolation for them, whiche ſuffer for theyr offences.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OF THEM</hi> whiche ſuffer for theyr euyll dedes,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> Peter ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, ſayinge: what prayſe is it, if whan ye be buffeted for your fau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, ye take it pacientely? And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> Se that none of you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer as a murtherer, or as a thefe, or as an yuell doer, or a buſy body in other mennes matters. But if it chaunce ſo, that we muſt ſuffer for an euyll dede doone of vs, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued puniſhemente maye be an holy ſufferynge, no leſſe pleaſaunt to god, than the ſufferynge of the innocent martyrs. For if the euyll doer confeſſe his ſynne before god, and beleue that his ſynne is forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, throughe Ieſu Chriſte: then by Ieſu Chriſte it is broughte to
<pb facs="tcp:10370:101"/> paſſe, that the deſerued punyſſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſanctified, to obteyne the crowne of euerlaſtyng glory: was not the thefe, ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging on the croſſe vpon the one ſyde of Chrſt, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in his puniſhement,<note place="margin">Luce. 22.</note> as ſoone as he aknowleged his ſynne, and throughe faythe commended his helthe to Chriſte? Was it not ſayd alſo to hym, This daye thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe? Neyther is it meruayle, that euyll dooers throughe faythe, can in theyr de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued puniſhementes, be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as innocent martyrs. For as the martyrs in theyr ſufferynge do teſtifie and witneſſe Chriſt and the goſpell, ſo euyll doers in theyr pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, do teſtifie and wytneſſe the lawe of god, and be examples to other, that they auoyde euyll dedes, leſt they be puniſhed in like
<pb facs="tcp:10370:101"/> maner. To be an example, that miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheuouſe dedes be auoyded, is it not a worke of holyneſſe? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whether a man do ſuffer iuſtly or vniuſtely, let hym beleue in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſte, and his ſufferynge ſhal cauſe hym to opteyne of the lord a garland that neuer ſhal wyther a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Therfore no man oughte to diſpeire.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> For Chriſte hath gyuen hym ſelfe a rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion for al. There is one god, and oone mediator of god and man, namely the manne Chriſt Ieſu, which gaue him ſelfe a ranſome for all men. Beholde, he ſayth for al. Therfore alſo, He wil,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.</note> that all retourne to repentaunce. And he ſaith,<note place="margin">Luc. 5.</note> I came not to cal the iuſte, but ſynners, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wold be borne. Iuda, Dauid,<note place="margin">Matth. 1.</note> Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, Thamar, Rachab, and Batſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba be examples. Therfore he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth
<pb facs="tcp:10370:102"/> the goſpell to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to euery creature.<note place="margin">Ezec. 18.</note> He wyl not the death of a ſynner, but the helth of al men. So he calleth al to him whiche be burdened.<note place="margin">Matt. 11. Luc. 19.</note> So he recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to hym zache. Maudelyn, Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, Matthei, the woman of Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nee.<note place="margin">Matth. 5. Matt. 27.</note> So he receyued to fauour the thefe. Alſo he apered after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection to Mary Maudelyne, out of whom he had expelled ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyuelles.<note place="margin">Matth. 16.</note> He admytteth and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth Thomas the harde beleuer. He conuerteth Saul beyng a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutour moſte greuouſe.<note place="margin">Acto. 9.</note> Brefely he refuſeth no man, he receyueth all that repente, with a fatherlye mynde. He ſheweth mercye, he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the repentaunte to his ſonne. Therfore he commandeth to pray,<note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> Let thy kyngdome come, forgyue vs our treſpaſes.<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> Alſo, what ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:10370:102"/> ye pray the father in my name, it ſhall be gyuen you. Aſke,<note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> and it ſhal be gyuen you: knocke: and it ſhall be opened vnto you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Sentences out of holy ſcripture, to ſtyrce vp a deſyre to dye.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVE</hi> are ſtrangers before the,<note place="margin">1. Par. 30.</note> as were all our fathers. Our days be as it were a ſhadowe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the erth, and here is none abiding. ¶The lyfe of man is a warfare vpon the erthe: and his days,<note place="margin">Iob. 7.</note> as the dayes of a hired ſeruaunt.</p>
                  <p>¶A man borne of a woman,<note place="margin">Iob. 14.</note> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge a ſhort tyme, is repleniſhed with moche myſery. He commeth forth lyke a flower, and goth away lyke a ſhadowe, and neuer remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in one eſtate.</p>
                  <p>¶What man is he that lyueth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 88.</note> &amp; ſhall not ſe deathe?</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10370:103"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 89.</note>¶Our yeres paſſen awaye as a cop webbe, the dayes of our age be three ſcore and ten, or in the chefeſt foure ſcore yeres, and the mooſte part of theſe, is labour and peyne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 101.</note>¶My dayes be waſted as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, and I am dryed vp as the graſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 144.</note>¶A man is made lyke to vanitie, his days paſſe away as a ſhadow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Eccle. 7.</note>¶The day of death is better then the daye of lyfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note>¶We haue not here a dwellynge citie, but we ſeke for one to come.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iaco. 4.</note>¶What is our lif? it is a vapour, aperynge a lyttell whyle, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde vaniſheth awaye.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note>¶All fleſhe is as hey, and all the glory of man as the flower of hey, the hey is dryed vp, and the flower falleth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:10370:103"/>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>¶THE TABLE OF THE</hi> fyrſte boke.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE</hi> preparation to the Croſſe, &amp; howe it muſt be pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly borne.</item>
               <item>¶What the Croſſe is Cap. 1.</item>
               <item>¶Two kindes of croſſes. Ca. 2.</item>
               <item>Howe the faithful be temted. 3.</item>
               <item>¶The Croſſe is of God onely. Cap. 4.</item>
               <item>Croſſe is the worke of the good wil of god. 5.</item>
               <item>¶The godly are the fyrſte that are afflycted of God, to theyr good and welthe. Cap. 6.</item>
               <item>¶In tribulation we muſte pray. Cap. 7.</item>
               <item>Of prayer, and the maner therof in tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <list>
                     <item>Whoſe prayers are harde of god.</item>
                     <item>The promyſe of god. Faythe.</item>
                     <item>To aſke in the name of Ieſu.</item>
                     <item>The affecte to deſyre any thynge.</item>
                     <item>Thankes gyuynge.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>¶We oughte to be patient in affliction, not to be angry, not to ſpeake euyll of god. Cap. 8.</item>
               <item>¶Soccur in affliction muſt be aſked of god. 9.</item>
               <item>¶Yet in affliction or ſyckeneſſe, medycine and councell are not to be deſpiſed. Ca. 10.</item>
               <item>In affliction no tyme may be apoynted to god, nor way wherby we wolde be delyuered. ca. 11.</item>
               <item>¶It is great comfort to them that be in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to remember, that Chriſt was alſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and exercyſed with yl, as we be wont. 12.</item>
               <item>¶It is great comfort in affliction, that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hurt the faithfull, except Chriſt wil. Ca. 13</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:10370:104"/>
               <item>¶The goodnes of god is not to be deſpyſed, or lightly regarded before afflictions, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by god wyll puniſhe &amp; gyue warning. Ca. 14.</item>
               <item>¶There be dyuerſe craftes of the dyuel, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by he tempteth, and where one crafte profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothynge, he addeth many other. Ca. 15.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ¶If thou be tempted in pryde, or vayenglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, anſwere hym agayne.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ¶If thou be tempted in wrothe or anger.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ¶If thou be tempted in feaſtynge, or glottony and dronkenneſſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ¶If thou be temted in auarice or couetouſnes.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ¶If thou be tempted with hunger, pouertie, or carefulnes of lyuynge.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> ¶If thou be tempted of idelnes.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> ¶If thou be temted of ſecurite.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> ¶If thou be temted of fornication &amp; adultery.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> ¶If thou be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with lying or light wordes</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> ¶If thou be temted of confeſſyng the goſpel, or ſufferynge perſecution for the goſpell.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> ¶If thou be temted of the faythe of thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes: as wherfore beleuefte thou not that, whiche thy forefathers haue beleued.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> ¶If thou be temted of ſtrange religyon, or of worſhypping of ſaynctes, or ymages, or men.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> ¶If thou muſt dye, and leaue wyfe, chyldren, and thy dere frendes.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> ¶If thou be tempted of condemnation, that thou arte condemned of god.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> ¶If the dyuel ſay, thou art a ſynner, and art
<pb facs="tcp:10370:104"/> not graffed in Chriſte.</item>
               <item>¶If he continue and ſay, but thy ſynnes paſſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> the ſonde of the ſea.</item>
               <item>¶If he ſay, ſuche promyſes are made to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> godly, but thou art an apoſtata, and a loſt man.</item>
               <item>But god hereth no ſinners nor ſtraiers away. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/>
               </item>
               <item>But thou comeſt very late with thy contricion. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/>
               </item>
               <item>¶But he had a ſtronge faythe in god, whiche <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> thou lackeſt.</item>
               <item>¶What if all holy ſcripture be falſe, for they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> were men, whiche ſpake it, and wrote it.</item>
               <item>¶If the temptator ſay, thou haſt not kepte the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> lawe of god, wherfore thou art accurſed.</item>
               <item>¶If he ſay thou muſt forſake the worlde. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The table of the ſeconde boke.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVHAT</hi> is deathe. Cap. 1.</item>
               <item>¶What is the cauſe of deathe. Ca. 2.</item>
               <item>¶Two maner of deathes. Cap. 2.</item>
               <item>¶To the electe and faythfull, eternall deathe by Chriſte is ouercome. Cap. 3.</item>
               <item>¶Although the godly die, yet they ſhal liue. 4.</item>
               <item>¶The deathe of the godly is a ſlepe. Cap. 5.</item>
               <item>Baptiſme is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort in the poynt of deathe. 6.</item>
               <item>¶The godly knowe the tyme of dyinge to be determined of god. Cap. 7.</item>
               <item>The vngodly lyue not out halfe theyr dayes. 8.</item>
               <item>¶The godly alſo in the tyme of hunger, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and warre, be puniſhed, and dye with the wycked. ca. 9.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:10370:105"/>
               <item>¶To whom they that dye ought to commyt theyr ſpirite. cap. 10.</item>
               <item>¶The body is buried, but it ſhall ryſe agayne in the laſte daye. ca. 11.</item>
               <item>¶In the panges of deathe, and in all tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the remedies be to be lerned of the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feraunce of Chriſte, cap. 12.</item>
               <item>¶The dieng, muſt be exhorted to forgiue. 13.</item>
               <item>¶Suche as be dienge ſhulde be admonyſſhed, that they receyue the ſacrament of Chriſtes body and bloude. ca. 14.</item>
               <item>¶Diuerſe conſolations, that the life and tyme of affliction is but ſhorte. ca. 15.</item>
               <item>¶The comfort of wydowes and Orphans.</item>
               <item>¶The comfort of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trauailing with child</item>
               <item>¶A comfort for them that lament the deade.</item>
               <item>¶A conſolation for theym, whiche ſuffer for theyr offences.</item>
               <item>¶Sentences out of holy ſcripture to ſtyrre vp a deſyre to dye.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶LONDINI in aedibus Thomae Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleti typis impreſſ. Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</p>
            <p>ANNO. M.D.XL.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10370:105"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
